<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>D. D. An advertisement, anent the reading of the books of Antonia Borignion By George White minister at Mary-Culter near Aberdeen.</title>
            <author>White, George, d. 1724.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 54 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65735</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1767</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222008</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833247</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833247</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37722</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65735)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37722)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2162:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>D. D. An advertisement, anent the reading of the books of Antonia Borignion By George White minister at Mary-Culter near Aberdeen.</title>
                  <author>White, George, d. 1724.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by John Forbes, printer to the town and University,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Aberdeen ;</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A1 is blank but for black-letter signature on recto.</note>
                  <note>With a preliminary index leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bourignon, Antoinette, 1616-1680 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Advertising --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37722:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>D. D. AN ADVERTISEMENT, Anent the Reading of the Books of <hi>Antonia Borignion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> GEORGE WHITE <hi>Miniſter at</hi> Mary-Culter <hi>near</hi> ABERDEEN.</p>
            <q>They have a Zeal of GOD, but not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Knowledge. <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 10.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>All Hereticks diminiſh the Authority of the Holy Scriptures. <bibl>
                  <hi>Tert. de praeſc. c. 49.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Enthuſiaſm is an Impiety, whereby a Perſon hardily bent for the Inward Worſhip of GOD, doth boldly violat and deſpiſe His Commands, as to outwards. <bibl>
                  <hi>Mr. Henry Scougall P: D: in Aeth: l: 4: c: 8: de juſtitia.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>ABERDEEN,</hi> Printed by JOHN FORBES, Printer to the TOWN and UNIVERSITY. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:37722:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37722:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37722:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37722:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:37722:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37722:4"/>
            <head>The <hi>TABLE</hi> or <hi>INDEX.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SECTIONS. SUBSECTION 1. NUM. POINTS. SUBS. 2. SECTIONS.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Sect. 1. <hi>The Occaſion and Purpoſe of the</hi> Advertiſement. page 1</item>
               <item>Sect. 2. <hi>How I have read her Books and the Rules of Arguing.</hi> p. 3</item>
               <item>Sect. 3. Q. <hi>If</hi> A. B. <hi>was Divinely Inſpired?</hi> p. 7
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>and</hi> Sect. 4. Subſ. 2. N. 2. p. 83</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 4. Q. <hi>If her Doctrine be conform to the Holy Scriptures?</hi> p. 23
<list>
                     <item>Subſ. 1. <hi>Of the Eſſentials of Religion.</hi> p. 24
<list>
                           <item>N. 1. <hi>Concerning GOD and the Bleſſed Trinity.</hi> p. 25</item>
                           <item>N. 2. <hi>Of CHRIST and his Satisfaction for Us.</hi> p. 31</item>
                           <item>N. 3. <hi>Of Mans future State.</hi> p. 40</item>
                           <item>N. 4. <hi>Anent the Love of GOD.</hi> p. 45</item>
                           <item>N. 5. <hi>Of the Holy Scriptures.</hi> p. 51</item>
                           <item>N. 6. <hi>Miſcelanies relating to the Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials of Religion.</hi> p. 53
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Whereof the</hi> 1. Point <hi>is, Of GOD'S Decrees and the Doctrines depending thereupon.</hi> p. 54</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:37722:5"/>
                     <item>2. <hi>Of the Image of GOD in Man.</hi> p. 60</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>If Man ſinned before he ſinned.</hi> p. 61</item>
                     <item>4. <hi>Of Perfection.</hi> p. 62</item>
                     <item>5. <hi>Of Perſeverance.</hi> p. 64</item>
                     <item>6. <hi>Anent the Sacraments.</hi> p. 66</item>
                     <item>7. <hi>Of Paſtors and Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> p. 69
<list>
                           <item>N. 1. <hi>Of Acceſſories in the general.</hi> p. 73</item>
                           <item>N. 2. <hi>Of</hi> A. Bs. <hi>Acceſsories in particular.</hi> p. 77</item>
                           <item>N. 3. <hi>Of her Contradictions.</hi> p. 89</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. 5. <hi>How Errours in Books ſhall be diſcerned?</hi> p. 92</item>
               <item>Sect. 6. <hi>If any ſhould read the Books of</hi> A. B.? p. 94</item>
               <item>Sect. 7. <hi>If</hi> Borignianiſts <hi>be a New Sect.</hi> p. 96</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:37722:5"/>
            <head>Information to the Reader.</head>
            <p>LEt the Reader of this little Book remember, that (for brevities ſake) the two Letters A. B. <hi>Signiſie</hi> Antonia Borignion.</p>
            <p>Ap. <hi>the</hi> Apologie <hi>for her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S. V. Solid Vertue.</p>
            <p>L. W. Light of the World.</p>
            <p>Pt. <hi>the Part of the Book that is cited.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:37722:6"/>
            <p>P. <hi>the Page thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And (according to the Table)</hi> Sect. <hi>the</hi> Section.</p>
            <p>Subſ. <hi>the</hi> Subſection.</p>
            <p>N. <hi>the</hi> Number <hi>of the</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſection.</p>
            <p>And Po. <hi>the</hi> Point <hi>of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. Queſtion. A. Anſwer.</p>
            <p>Obj. Objection.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37722:6"/>
               <head>SECTION I. <hi>The Occaſion and Purpoſe of this</hi> Advertiſement.</head>
               <p>HAving obſerved with Regrate, for ſeveral Years bygone, ſundry well-meaning Perſons, (and ſome of them not Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned) to have vented many Errours, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> the <hi>Gospell-Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Church-Government,</hi> the <hi>Paſtorall-Office,</hi> and other moſt Sacred Eſtabliſhments of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> which they had pick't out of the <hi>Pamphlets</hi> that are ſaid to be written be <hi>A. B. a Flandrian:</hi> Yea ſome young men of good expectation, by reading theſe books inadvertent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, had their Melancholy height'ned to an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive degree, therefore it ſeemed good, for the Truths ſake (which we ought to contend for <hi>Jude</hi> 3) and for preventing, by the LORD's Bleſſing, further inconvenience that way; to write a ſeaſonable <hi>Advertiſement,</hi> in meekneſs and love, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.14. <hi>That we be no more child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren toſſed to and fro, and carried about with every winde of Doctrine by the ſleight of men and cunning craftineſs, whereby they lie in wait to deceive.</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:37722:7"/>That Chriſtian People may not through blind zeal ſnatch up any pretence of piety without due examination; and it often fals out, that ſome out of a Capricious fancie of defending Innovations, leave the high and troden way to Heaven, &amp; ſo wander in a Wilderneſs of Errours.</p>
               <p>It is here propoſed, that all who tender their Souls Intereſt, may in this caſe obſerve the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Oracle <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17 18. <hi>To mark them which cauſe diviſions and offences contrary to the Doctrine which they have received, and avoid them, who with good words and fair ſpeeches deceive the hearts of the Simple.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Tractat</hi> ſhall be ſhort, and ſo not tedious to any Reader; becauſe in a late Apologie for <hi>A. B.</hi> printed at <hi>London Anno</hi> 1699, two pious and learned men <hi>(to wit) Dr. John Cockburn</hi> and the Author of the <hi>Snake in the Graſs,</hi> and the <hi>Hiſtory of Sin and Herefie</hi> are fiercely attaucked, for writting againſt her; who doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs (if alive) will anſwer for themſelves; which yet will require a conſiderable time for them to anſwer all the Defences which the <hi>Ap.</hi> hath alleadged for <hi>A. B.</hi> and her Abetters, her whole Life, Actions and Writtings: So my preſent undertaking is only to act the pairt of their fore-runner, as one who doth what he can to ſtop the progreſs of devouring Fire, till great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er power arrive to extinguiſh it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37722:7"/>
               <head>SECTION II. <hi>How I have read her Books, and the Rules of Arguing.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEfore I come to adduce the Rules of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting, it is to be noticed how the <hi>Ap.</hi> in his Preface declares that he is perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his Conſcience, that the Writtings of <hi>A. B.</hi> tend to the reviving of the Spirit of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; Which can have no more force to perſwade others to be of his Opinion, than the Canting Inſinuations of the Bygots of all Parties, declaring, aſſevering and ſwearing, that them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves only are in the Right, and their Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites in the wrong. A mans erring Conſcience cannot oblidge himſelf to believe a Lye, or to do ill things, it only binds him for to uſe the means to get it better informed, and far leſs ſhould ſuch a vehement Proteſtation of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious Perſwaſion of the goodneſs of ſuch rare Teneds, as are here queſtioned, procure the Aſſent of Rational men, but the ſolidity of his Reaſons (if he hath any) according to the Scripture, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15.16.</p>
               <p>There are four Rules of reading Books aright, and judging of the Authors Sentiments, or there are ſo many Poſtulats pre-required to the right diſputing of any matter, as they are ſet down in the <hi>Ap. Pt.</hi> 4, <hi>p.</hi> 334.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:37722:8"/>
               <p n="1">1 To be well acquainted with what we cenſure.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If the Scope of <hi>A. Bs.</hi> Writtings be good and agreeable to the main end of Religion, in that caſe to bear with litle eſcapes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To read her Books without prejudice, or an evil eye.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To narrate and interpret faithfully.</p>
               <p>All which Rules (he alleadgeth) theſe gentlmen have tranſgreſſed, who did write againſt <hi>A. B.</hi> And to obviat ſuch an Objection againſt my ſelf, I have obſerved and ſhall firmly adhere unto the third and fourth of theſe Rules without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; being ſo far from having a Prejudice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>A. B.</hi> and her Abetters, that I wiſh with meek <hi>Moſes, Numb.</hi> 11.29. <hi>That all the Lords People were Prophets, and that the Lord would put his Spirit upon them.</hi> And the Teneds or Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents which I intend to examine ſhall be truly narrated, either in the expreſs words of <hi>A. B.</hi> and her <hi>Ap.</hi> or the import thereof, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſtortion.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Rule, needs ſome Qualifications, for a good Purpoſe doth not juſtifie an evil Action, no more than <hi>Sauls ſparing the Cattel of the Amalekits</hi> contrary to GOD's command, pretending that he did ſo, <hi>For the good purpoſe of Sacrificeing</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.21.22. Neither ſhould Books be approven, in which Errours are mixed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37722:8"/>with Verities, ſince evil is through any defect, but good, from the intire cauſe. So I diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh this Rule, if a Writter having a good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign miſtake in a few things of no great moment, and upon ſound Advice will revoke his Errours, I grant this ſhould be favourably interpreted; but if the Errours be groſs and many, and the Author boaſting of being Divinely inſpired in writting them, and to have had more Light and Piety then all men, in that caſe, I deny that ſuch miſtakes ſhould paſs uncenſured.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, as to the firſt of the four Pre-conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions for diſputing, that we ſhould be well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with what we cenſure, that is a very good Rule, and by it the <hi>Ap.</hi> ſeems to inſult his Opponents, that either they did not well know the <hi>French Language</hi> in which <hi>A. B.</hi> wrote, or had not read all her <hi>Twenty two</hi> Books. So not only the <hi>Ap.</hi> but likewiſe all that own <hi>A. B.</hi> whenſoever her Errours are mentioned, they anſwer warmly, that whatſoever ſeemeth hard in ſome of her Writtings is explained in others, which the cenſurers either have not read, or will not be at the pains to compare places together.</p>
               <p>Now to ward of this thruſt, the Reader ſhall be judge, if I cenſure any thing of <hi>A. Bs.</hi> Writtings, but what I underſtand well enough, having had ſufficient means for it, by reading
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37722:9"/>ſundry of her writtings, and particularly, <hi>The Light of the World,</hi> which is held for the chiefeſt of them all, and the ſtandard of all, both be herſelf and <hi>Poiret;</hi> ſee the admonition prefaced thereto by <hi>P. P. p.</hi> 36. And now I have read the <hi>Ap.</hi> which is aequivalent to the reading of all her Books, ſince the Author hath read them all, and defends all, and if I quarrel nothing but what he mantains, it were a frivolous ſhift to bid me go and ſearch any of <hi>A. Bs.</hi> Books for any explication of her Opinions. And if there be reall Errours and Contradictions found in her writtings, what explications can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move them?</p>
               <p>To conclude this <hi>Section,</hi> I ſhall to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid four, add other three rules of arguing, and eſpecially anent Points of Divinity.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To explain the Termes and ſtate the Queſtion aright.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To reaſon and anſwer candidly without Sophiſtry or Deceit.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To ſeek Verity rather than victory, and therefore though we may juſtly commend ſome good things in any Perſon or his writtings, not to mantain their Errours and Evtravagancies, which if through fondneſs we have failed in, upon ſecond thoughts to do ſo no more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:37722:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>SECTION III. <hi>If</hi> A. B. <hi>was Divinely inſpired.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> THis Queſtion cannot be well reſolved, untill the Terms thereof be cleared in the firſt place, and the Queſtion be rightly ſtated according to my firſt Rule; for unleſs this be done, all abrupt diſputs turn to a meer <hi>Logomachie,</hi> or a proud and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant doting about Queſtions and ſtrife of words which God expreſly forbids, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.4.</p>
               <p>Divine Inſpiration is taken in very different Senſes, for,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> in a large ſenſe, every man may be ſaid to be Divinely Inſpired, becauſe of his Rational Soul, which was made after the Image of God <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7. <hi>God breathed into Mans Noſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirls the Breath of Life,</hi> and Gods breathing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Man is a Divine Inſpiration.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. One is ſaid to be Divinely Inſpired, to whom God giveth a capacity, Genius or fitneſs for an Office or Imployment, as it is written <hi>Judg.</hi> 3.10. <hi>The Spirit of the Lord came upon Othniel, and he judged Iſrael and went out to Warre;</hi> ſo it is a neceſſary Qualification of a Biſhop that he be <hi>Apt to teach,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3 2. and the Holy Ghoſt maketh Biſhops, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. Yea this is aſcribed to men of <hi>Manuary Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings,</hi> as to <hi>Bezalcel</hi> and with him <hi>Aholiab, Exod.</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:37722:10"/>31.3. <hi>I have filled him with the Spirit of God, in Wiſdom, and in all manner of workmanſhip for the tabernacle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3ly. A Spiritual man judgeth not of Divine things by carnal reaſon, Church Authority only, Tradition or Cuſtom, but according to the Truth and Minde of God, revealed in the Scriptures, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.15. <hi>But the Spiritual man judgeth all things,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Job</hi> 32.8. <hi>The Inſpiration of the Almighty giveth man Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi> Which <hi>Apothegme</hi> may alſo be referred to the former ſenſe, that God qualifies and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth every perſon whom he commiſſioneth for any Imployment, as, to teach others: Yea, perſons unregenerated may have ſomething like to this <hi>Orthodoxie,</hi> as that underſtanding Scribe, who in Conference with the Lord, did give the true and Spiritual ſenſe of the Law, upon whom it was accordingly pronounced, <hi>That he was not far from the Kingdom of God. Mark,</hi> 12.34. Yet being at a diſtance from true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, all the knowledge he had, was only by the common illumination of the Spirit, which and other common gifts of the uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, whether they differ ſpecifically or gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually only, from the ſaving knowledge and graces of the Godly, I ſhall not here abide to determine.</p>
               <p n="4">4ly. Every Pious Perſon, is led by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37722:10"/>of God, both in his Converſion, when Gods Spirit enlightneth the Underſtanding and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neweth their Will, and likewiſe afterwards, directing and quickning to all Duty, which Light and Grace he beſtows in ſuch meaſures as fitteth the work wherein He in his Infinite Wiſdom imployes them; as, reading the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Praying, Preaching, Writting, doing of good Works, and ſuffering, (when called there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to:) Of this the Holy Spirit is the efficient cauſe, he bids us do well, <hi>Yet it is God who worketh in us both to will and to do, of his good pleaſure. Phil.</hi> 2.12.13. ſo 1 <hi>John,</hi> 2.20. <hi>Ye have an unction from the Holy One, and ye know all things.</hi> And this Illumination is by <hi>Divines</hi> called Subjective Revelation, becauſe of the agreement betwixt our Souls and the Divine aſſiſtance, and to diſtinguiſh it from the pretended <hi>Enthuſiaſm</hi> of deluded. Perſons, who boaſt of new Revelations, as the chief Rule of their Faith and Manners. And in this ſenſe <hi>Luther, Zuinglius</hi> and other Divines, who are cited in <hi>Quakeriſm no Popery, from pag.</hi> 19. are to be underſtood, when they write that the inward word of God, and the dictats of the Holy Spirit are the true word of God, which profit unto Salvation: which is alſo the Senſe and meaning of the ancient Holy Fathers, when they ſpeak of the leading of the Spirit
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37722:11"/>of God; as <hi>S. Chryſ.</hi> upon <hi>John</hi> 6.63. Chriſts words are to be heard according to the Spirit, <hi>And whoſo heareth them after a carnal manner profiteth nothing.</hi> And <hi>S. Cypr. de S. ſancto. p.</hi> 485. <hi>edit. Par. cum Annot. Ja. Pamel.</hi> Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, Inſpiration, and Aſpiration in the Godly, they have from the Holy Spirit the cauſe and effect, Matter and Increaſe.</p>
               <p n="5">5ly. The Prophets and Penmen of the Holy Scriptures were in a ſtrict ſenſe Divinely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. <hi>They ſpake as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 16.17. <hi>All Scriptures is given by the Inſpiration of God</hi> &amp;c. The Prophets and Apoſtles were without any previous Ratiocination of themſelves, power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully moved by God both to Teach and Write the Rule of Faith and Manners, and that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly both as to Matter and Words; which they proved to be immediat Objective Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, or rather Gods word than their own, (1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.13.) by the gift of Tongues, Miracles, Oracles, Viſions, diſcovering of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, foretelling things to come, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of men to God, beyond and above the ordinary Humane Means. The phraſe thus explained, I come to ſtate and anſwer the <hi>Queſtion,</hi> to wit, if <hi>A. B.</hi> was Divinely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired. The <hi>Ap.</hi> ſpends the third part of his Treatiſe (being 38 leaves) aiming to prove,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37722:11"/>that <hi>A. B.</hi> was led by the Spirit of God, or (what is the ſame on the matter) divinely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired, but never ſhewing, in what ſenſe or meaning, he would have the World believe that ſhe was ſo; and therefore all diſcourſing to that purpoſe, looks too like a continued <hi>Sophiſm,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called <hi>Ignorantio Elenchi,</hi> or a <hi>Fallacious way of arguing,</hi> ſeeming to prove the thing intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by an hudle of pretended Arguments, which yet conclude nothing as to the main point under Debate. <hi>Viz.</hi> In what ſenſe or reſpect he allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth his <hi>A. B.</hi> to have been Divinely inſpired.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Which now to examine particularly, I grant, that ſhe was Divinely Inſpired, in the firſt of the five reſpects forementioned <hi>i. e.</hi> She had a Rational Soul, if ever there was ſuch a perſon as <hi>A. B.</hi> (which ſome doubt of, who lived in <hi>Flanders</hi> about the time ſhe is ſaid to have been at <hi>Liſle,</hi> and yet heard nothing of her) but this is not all which the party means by her being Divinely inſpired, ſince ſhe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to more than an ordinary Spirit.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is more to be doubted, if ſhe was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely inſpired in the ſecond ſenſe, <hi>(to wit)</hi> if ſhe was fitted and well qualified for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and imployment that ſhe ſet out for in the World, which was three fold, the Miſtris of a Familie, a School-Miſtris, and a Propheteſs or a Teacher to reform all Mankind. There
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37722:12"/>is but little evidence given in her own writtings of he Diſcretion and far leſs of Divine inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in guiding either her School or Family; (tho ſhe pretended to the knowledge of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Spirits, and the very thoughts of peoples hearts <hi>Pref.</hi> to <hi>L. W. p.</hi> 41) for ſhe teſtifieth of her ſelf, <hi>S. V pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 196. how all her 32 Scholars at <hi>Liſle</hi> were in Actual compact with the Devil, and yet did very well what ſhe taught them. Alſo the <hi>Ap.</hi> writes of her, <hi>pt.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 323. that all her Servants were Witches and for a long time deſigned to murder her for her Riches; yet mentioneth nothing that ever ſhe diſmiſſed them before her Death.</p>
               <p>And if ſhe had a Prophetical Spirit that ſhall be tryed anon.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third and fourth Reſpects may be conſidered together, whereanent I charitably think that <hi>A. B.</hi> was a pious perſon, and ſo was led by the Spirit of God, as any other godly perſon is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1.</p>
               <p>But this conceſſion will not ſatisfie the <hi>Ap.</hi> who holds her to have been incomparably holy, and to have exceeded in knowledge the greateſt Divines, <hi>pt.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 240.241. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for her pretenſion muſt be tryed in another ſenſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> How can ſhe be called pious, who wrote many Errours, and was very proud and Uncharitable?</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:37722:12"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. She ſpake aright of Religion in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry things, which might have been by Divine Conduct, but in her Miſtakes and Errours, ſhe was led by her own ſpirit. <hi>Ap. p.</hi> 216.217. As ſhe confeſſeth in another Caſe, when ſhe was deluded by <hi>St. Saulien p.</hi> 239. And it is probable, that ſhe intended not to have written Lies or Fopperies, which happened either through her want of the means of true Knowledge, or the neglecting thereof; as the Reading of the Holy Spriptures, and Syſtems of Divinity, and medling with things too high for her, <hi>Pſ</hi> 131.1.</p>
               <p>She might have been Pious tho not pefect, and perſons ought to be charactered from their better pairt, and not from the worſt; from the ſet of their Spirit and tract of their Life, rather than from particular Actions or Eſcapes, and eſpecially, if they endeavour to diſcover and mortifie all Sins in themſelves.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This <hi>Obj.</hi> might be eaſily anſwered in the opinion of <hi>A. B.</hi> that Saints may apoſtatiſe totally and finally, even they who have attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to perfection, and could keep all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God. Which is defended be the <hi>Ap. pt.</hi> 2. <hi>p</hi> 136. (which yet is a groſs Errour, as ſhall afterward be ſhown) for according to her <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> it might follow, that ſhe wrote only Truth, ſhe was Humble and Charitable, ſo long as ſhe continued in the ſtate of Grace,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37722:13"/>but wrote her Errours, became Proud and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable, how ſoon ſhe loſt the Grace of God and fell into the eſtate of Damnation.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As to the fifth Senſe or Conſideration of the Conduct of the Spirit of God, which is the publick and ordinary acceptation of it, namely, a Prophetick infallible Spirit.</p>
               <p>This I poſitively affirm, <hi>A. B.</hi> had not in her writtings, and ſo the Queſtion is anſwered Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gativly, in Opoſition to the affirmation of <hi>A. B.</hi> and her <hi>Ap.</hi> and it is thus proved.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Holy Scriptures which were written by the Holy Prophets and Apoſtles, have a ſelf Evidence in them, ſhewing themſelves to be the Word of God, or the Dictats of the Holy Spirit; <hi>to wit,</hi> the matchleſs Sublimity of the matter, the Holineſs, Purity, and Harmony of the whole; the Efficacie or effectual working for converting Souls to God, beſids their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation from the Pen-mens ſpeaking of all Languages which they had never heard nor learned, and other Miracles accompanying them, extraordinary Viſions, ſure Prophecies, the Antiquity and preſervation of the ſamen, and the Confeſſion of Adverſaries.</p>
               <p>But <hi>A. Bs.</hi> writtings have nothing the like Confirmation, and therefore ſhe had no Divine Inſpiration in writting them.</p>
               <p>The Major is granted by all Chriſtians, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37722:13"/>the Minor is alſo clear, ſince neither <hi>A. B.</hi> nor her <hi>Ap.</hi> pretend to ſuch Teſtimonys tho their pretence be very high.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Scriptures written be men Divinely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired, are a perfect Rule in Religion, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us how to glorifie God and be ſaved our ſelves 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3 16.17. <hi>That the man of God may be prrfect.</hi> And we are to hold them accurſed, who would add to this Canon <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22 18. Therefore <hi>A. B.</hi> dare not pretend to ſuch inſpiration under pain of the curſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> You have wronged <hi>A. B.</hi> by miſtateing the Queſtion, for ſhe did not pretend to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie, or to write by an Infallible Spirit, as the Prophets and Apoſtles did; but only to interpret the Scriptures, to live well and to teach others to do ſo, <hi>L W. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 133. There ſhe promiſeth to write a <hi>Commentary</hi> upon the whole Scriptures, tho ſhe never performed it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, denying the Charge, for ſhe is not wronged by me, nor the Queſtion miſtated, ſince it is the ordinary and received Senſe of the Phraſe, to be Divinely Inſpired, or to be led by the Spirit of God in writting, to write by an Infallible Spirit, as the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did, who were the Amanuenſes of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Though ſhe durſt not ſpeak it out in plain
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37722:14"/>Terms, that ſhe acclaimed no leſs than ſuch a Spirit as the <hi>Prophets and Apoſtles</hi> had (leſt the Readers at the firſt ſight, had cryed fy u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon her, for Blaſphemie,) but goes on in Clouds and Darkneſs, never declaring in what Senſe ſhe was Divinely inſpired, yet, I ſay, on the matter ſhe acclaimed no leſs, for theſe Reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt becauſe, when it was objected to her by Divines, that ſhe had not ſuch Knowledge as the Prophets had, and wrought no Miracles; ſhe ſhifted to give any direct anſwer, but ſlily ſtrived to diminiſh their Credit, and of the Holy Scriptures, alſo, alleadging that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets knew not all things which they wrote, that all of them wrought not Miracles, that the Devil had opened the eyes of the blind and raiſed the Dead, and that the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was miſtaken, (I tremble relating it) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent the <hi>Fig Tree Mat.</hi> 11.19. <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 136. <hi>Ap. p.</hi> 168.203.204.205.206. and 222.223. All which Calumnies might be eaſily refuted, but I leave that Task to thoſe who are writting againſt them more Copiouſly.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The very Title of her Book is Blaſphem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, to wit, <hi>The Light of the World,</hi> which is the Epithite given to CHRIST, and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and in aſſuming that Title ſhe equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſeth her ſelf to them, tho injuriouſly.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:37722:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p n="3">3. It is evident, that ſhe pretended to ſuch a Spirit as the Apoſtles had, when ſhe affirmed, that ſhe could write ſuch a Book as the <hi>New Teſtament, L. W. pt.</hi> 1 <hi>p</hi> 133. Now if ſhe could have ſo written, then ſhe could have done it either by a fallible or infallible Spirit, if only by a fallible Spirit, then it could not have been ſuch a Book, but if by an infallible Spirit, then ſhe acclaimed ſuch a Spirit as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles had, which the Objector denyes.</p>
               <p>Many more Inſtances might be adduced to this purpoſe, but theſe may ſuffice.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I anſwer to the grand <hi>Objection,</hi> that ſhe pretended not to write a New Canon or Rule of Faith, but only to expound the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; giving but not granting, that her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions did run no higher, that ſame is too high. The <hi>Quakers</hi> acknowledge, that their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is ſomewhat inferiour to the Prophets; <hi>Quakeriſm no Popery p.</hi> 32.33 <hi>Mr. G. K.</hi> The learned Author whereof is no Quaker now) Yea the Roman Church it ſelf would be offended, if any man ſhould ſay, that they coine new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets in Religion, or that they did more by their Dogmatiſing, then to expound the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and diſpenſe the Churches Traditions (but by a Prophetical Light and Divine influence) as their doctrine in this point is well collected by <hi>Amyrald in Theſ. Salmur: de aut Script: n.</hi> 15.16.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:37722:15"/>
               <p>So for <hi>A. B.</hi> to pretend Divine Conduct to expound the Scriptures better than all others, is too great Arrogancie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Will you not allow, <hi>A. B.</hi> to have had more of Divine Conduct than you have done alreadie, that poſſibly ſhe had it only in ſome things, which ſhe did and taught, as ordinarily every Godly Perſon hath in what he does aright?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I have granted enough in the ſaid Terms, and more I cannot, becauſe, it is ſufficiently proved, that ſhe was not Divinely inſpired, as the Pen-men of the Holy Scriptures were; either to add to the Canonical Books or to interpret Scripture infallibly, as they did, neither was ſhe led by the Divine Spirit, as an ordinary Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer in the Church, to interpret and apply the Scriptures (which is Preaching) ſince ſhe was not fitted for that end, by the means of Gods appointment, nor yet obſerved the Rules thereof <hi>Neh.</hi> 8.8. <hi>Ezra</hi> the Scribe, with the Prieſts and Levits, read in the Book of the Law diſtinctly, and gave the ſenſe, and made the People to underſtand the reading. <hi>Timothy</hi> the Evangeliſt was enjoined Reading 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13. and ſince his Days, all Holy and Wiſe Men who interpret the Scriptures pray to God for the Direction of his Spirit, which indyted them, that they may Prophecie, according to the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37722:15"/>Proportion of Faith <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6. They com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare Scripture with Scripture, and look to the Scope of the place, they ſtudy the Languages in which the Scriptures were firſt written, Hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories likewiſe and Cuſtoms of ſeveral Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, Proverbial Speeches, and famous Writters of them, which are often cited, and frequent Alluſions made thereto in the Holy Scriptures, they read the <hi>Creeds, Confeſſions of Faith, Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſms</hi> and <hi>Syſtems of Divinity</hi> of the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Churches both Ancient and Modern; they ſearch for Truth by the Literal Senſe of the whole Scriptures, pondering well whether or no, the ſpeech be in Terms proper to the things treated of, or borrowed from other things which is called a figurative Speech.</p>
               <p>By theſe and the like means the ſettled and ordinary Teachers, and Expoſitors of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures doe, begging the bleſſing of God, Humb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Aſſiduouſly endeavour, to be fitted for the great and Sacred function, of labouring in the Word and Doctrine.</p>
               <p>But <hi>A. B.</hi> does not ſo much as pretend to uſe theſe means, nor yet to expound the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, by the true Rules, but on the Contrary, ſhe laid by the Scriptures and contemned all Syſtems of Divinity and other helps of Learning.</p>
               <p>Therefore ſhe was not fit or qualified to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the Scriptures, even as an ordinary
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37722:16"/>Teacher. So ſince <hi>A. B.</hi> was not led by the Spirit of God, to write her Books, and expound the Scriptures, either in an Ordinary, or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary way: It remains then, that ſhe performed theſe things by no other Faculty, but by Gueſſing and vain Divination, nor can I add a Fourth Member to this Tripartite Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion; tho poſſibly the fertile Brain of a new <hi>Ap.</hi> will gender one, ſhewing how one can be led by the Spirit of God to write, not by an Infallible Spirit, nor as an Ordinary Teacher, nor yet to be a Meer Gueſſer or pretender to it, which (as the Roman Proverb was) <hi>Let the credulous Jew believe, not I.</hi>)</p>
               <p>To put a Period to this long Section, I ſhall produce all the pretended Reaſons, which the <hi>Ap pt.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 240 and 241. Alleadgeth, for proving <hi>A. B.</hi> to have been Divinely Inſpir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſhall anſwer them ſeverally, as if they had been Objected againſt my Concluſion on this Head.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 1. Her Doctrine was conform to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, therefore ſhe was Divinely Inſpired.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. Denying the Antecedent, for her Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine was moſtly contrary to the Scriptures, as (God willing) ſhall be Manifeſted in the next Section.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I deny likewiſe the Conſequence, becauſe a perſons Doctrine may be conform to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37722:16"/>who had no extraordinary Inſpiration.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. She was Unlearned and yet exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the greateſt Divines.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. She exceeded them only in Vanity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>George Fox</hi> was unlearned, ſo he gave it out, that all his Divinity was revealed to him among the Hils of <hi>Lancaſter.</hi> And <hi>Jacob Bhemen,</hi> the pretended illuminated Sutor wrote ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Books like <hi>A. Bs.</hi> yet none of them was Divinely Inſpired.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. Inſtance.</hi> How could an unlearned Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon write as ſhe did without Divine Inſpiration?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. It is much doubted, if <hi>Poiret</hi> or ſome other man wrote not theſe Books, that are ſaid to be hers.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is very conceavable, how one Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, but of a Melancholly Temper, and Luxuriant Fancie; might write ſuch Books, getting Terms of Art by Converſe with Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men, and a Schem and Copy of their Fancies and high flown Notions, by reading ſome of theſe called <hi>Myſtiches,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Theu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,</hi> and <hi>Joannes à Cruce,</hi> yet without Divine Inſpiration.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj</hi> 3. She wrote without premeditation, and did neither correct nor read over what ſhe once wrote?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That is not like to be true, yet if it was indeed ſo, then her writtings are ſomuch the worſe.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:37722:17"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj</hi> 4. She had no Worldly aim, therefore &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Many pretended <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> ſeemed to have as little, who yet were not Divinely Inſpired.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 5. She reached the Conſciences of Others, therefore &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All <hi>Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Shiſmaticks</hi> have the like pretenſion, accounting the People of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, the only Inlightned and Godly Party, having the <hi>Old Gnoſticks</hi> for their Patrons, in Monopoliſing Godlineſs to themſelves, <hi>Iren.</hi> L. 1. <hi>G.</hi> 1. ſee <hi>Corſe, inſtr. L.</hi> 1. <hi>C.</hi> 37. and L. 14.2.1. whereas, the truly Orthodox rather make one Chriſtian, than an hundred of their Opinion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 6. Her Writtings had no contradiction in them, therefore &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It ſhall be ſhown ſhe had, in the next Section, as for Example, on this preſent Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. She affirmed that one might know by his Natural Spirit, her ſelf to be Divinely In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired, <hi>Ap. pt.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 197 But againſt that <hi>p.</hi> 200. None can diſcern her to be Divinely Inſpired, who is not ſo himſelf; now to know a certain thing by the Natural Spirit, and not to know it thereby, is a Contradiction, but to know by the Natural, and not to know but by the Divine Spirit, is to know and not to know by the Natural Spirit, which is a clear Contradiction of her ſelf, whereas GOD's Spirit cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37722:17"/>Himſelf, He being Truth it ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 7. She had a Pious Life and taught rare Penitence, therefore &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. St. Aug. Epiſ.</hi> 106. accounts that <hi>Pelagius</hi> the <hi>Arch Heretick,</hi> deceived many by the ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Life and Doctrine; ſo he taught the Doctrine, revived now by <hi>A. B.</hi> That riches ſhould be abandoned, and that we can by a ſtrict penitence merit remiſſion of ſins, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 8. <hi>A. B.</hi> affirmed, that ſhe was Divine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Inſpired, therefore &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> But I have proven the contrary, therefore, ſhe was not Divinely Inſpired.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECTION. IV. Q. <hi>If the Doctrine of</hi> A. B. <hi>be conform to the Holy Scriptures.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> THis is the ſecond Material Head in this Tractate, for if it be true which is often written be <hi>A. B.</hi> and her <hi>Ap.</hi> That her Doctrine is agreeable to the Holy Scriptures (which are the only Publick Standard of Truth) then it would be moſt injurious, for any man to offer to give Chek unto it: Therefore I hope, it will be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37722:18"/>no leſs profitable than pleaſant to the Readers, that this be fairly put to the Teſt, and if it appear, upon an impartial inquirie, that (not a little) but very much of <hi>A. Bs.</hi> Doctrine, be alien from and contrary to the Scriptures, it may happily prove an Antidote for ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous People that they ſwallow not down her Poiſonous Errours, together with her Varniſht Pretenſions to Devotion and Piety, for to write Errours pretending to be Divinely Inſpired, makes the ſin the more hainous, to father Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths upon the Spirit of Truth.</p>
               <div n="1" type="subsection">
                  <head>SUBSECTION I. <hi>Anent the Eſſentials of Religion.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe eſſence of any thing is, that which we conceive in the firſt place, as the definitive <hi>Idea,</hi> or formal Notion of it, and without which, it could not be ſuch a being; as the Soul and Body are the Eſſential Parts of Man; ſo the Eſſentials of Religion are theſe moſt neceſſary and fundamentall Truths, which if any Perſon diſown, he is accounted an <hi>Atheiſt</hi> or <hi>Heretick,</hi> and none of the True Religion.</p>
                  <p>In the beginning of the next <hi>Subſection</hi> I
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37722:18"/>purpoſe (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) to conſider the <hi>Aps.</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, of Eſſential and Acceſſory Verities, and at the preſent (for diſpatching's ſake) ſhall admit of his Definition of the Eſſentials of Religion <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. that they are ſuch Truths without the Expreſs Knowledge and Belief of which, none can be eternally ſaved.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A. B.</hi> and the <hi>Ap</hi> profeſs that they own the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> and that they are content, that her Doctrine be entirely tryed by the <hi>Holy Scriptures, L. W. Pref. to the Engliſh Reader,</hi> now their Knowledge and Ingenuity in that main Point (whether or no their Doctrine be agreeable to the Scripture and the Creed which is collected therefrom) ſhall be brought to the tryal diſtinctly in the ſubſequent part of this Section.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="number">
                     <head>SECTION. IV. SUBS. I. N. I. <hi>Concerning GOD and the Bleſſed Trinity.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe word <hi>Religion</hi> is taken from a Latine word <hi>Religando,</hi> Binding, for it is an Holy Law or Doctrine binding or
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37722:19"/>obliedging Man to worſhip and ſerve GOD, and binding us to Him for our own Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                     <p>It is the Chief thing in <hi>Religion</hi> to have true Knowledge of GOD in order to the glorifying of Him, and next to that, how we ſhall be happy by Him. <hi>John</hi> 17.3. <hi>This is Life Eternal, that they may know Thee, the only true GOD, and JESUS CHRIST whom thou haſt ſent. Heb.</hi> 11.6. <hi>For he that cometh to GOD muſt believe that He is, and that He is a rewarder of them that diligently ſeek Him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But <hi>A. B.</hi> had not a right notion of GOD Almighty, when ſhe wrote, that man is made as a little God in his Divine nature incloſed in his humanity. Our Souls are little Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities. The Soul is GOD, and GOD is the Soul. We are not to ſeek GOD without us. GOD made us Deities depending upon Him. The Church is an inviſible Spirit, and the Church is GOD himſelf. <hi>S. V. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 54.75. <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 42.53 110.111.113. and <hi>pt.</hi> 3 <hi>p.</hi> 92. Such Doctrine cannot abide the Teſt of the Holy Scriptures, which teach us, that GOD is the moſt perfect Being, moſt Simple, Infinite, Immenſe, Immutable, Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent, and Eternal, whereof the contrary properties are in the Creatures, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.4 <hi>The
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37722:19"/>LORD our GOD is one LORD.</hi> But if the Church or the Soul of man be GOD, then there muſt be more Gods then One, which to affirm, were blaſphemous and hereticall.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Ap. p.</hi> 52. attempts to anſwer this, citing <hi>John</hi> 17.21. and thence infering, that ſeeing man may have ſome ſort of union with GOD, <hi>A. Bs.</hi> words may be favourably In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted.</p>
                     <p>That is but a weak ſubterfuge, for the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Author doubtleſs knows, that the Text <hi>John</hi> 17.21. and its Parallels, do not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe <hi>A. Bs.</hi> foreſaid language, for CHRISTS praying, <hi>That Believers might be one in Him, and one among themſelves,</hi> imports only, their being Members of His Myſtical Body, that, thereby they might recover the Image of GOD, Knowledge and Holineſs, and be ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented one with another in love; but from this, no Scripture language, nor any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Commentator, neither any wiſe man did ever infer, that men ſhould be called GOD; Unleſs he would vouch the <hi>Manichees</hi> for his Authors, who were vile Hereticks, and held that there were two Gods, one good and another evil; they, indeed taught <hi>That the Soul of man was of the ſubſtance of GOD;</hi> As did other blaſphemous Hereticks, <hi>to wit,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37722:20"/>Cerdonians, Marcionites, and Priſcillianiſts</hi> which we have faithfully accounted by a moſt truſtie and diligent, antiquary: <hi>Forbes of Corſe in his Inſtr. hiſt. Theol. Li.</hi> 4. <hi>C.</hi> 5. <hi>N.</hi> 12. Citing alſo the Orthodox, who refuted them. Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>St. Ambroſe, Aug. Theodoret</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>And how can the unlearned Readers of <hi>A. Bs.</hi> writtings diſtinguiſh her Opinion from theirs in this prime and eſſential part of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion?</p>
                     <p>Likewiſe <hi>A. B.</hi> denyes GOD'S Attribute of Omniſcience (tho to deny any of his Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, be to deny GOD himſelf) when ſhe taught, that GOD doth not foreſee all future Actions of a free agent which is defended by the <hi>Ap. pt.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 127. 128. 129.</p>
                     <p>This is contrary to the Scriptures, <hi>John</hi> 21.17. <hi>LORD thou knoweſt all things. Pſalm.</hi> 139.2. <hi>Thou knoweſt my down ſitting and mine upriſing, thou underſtandeſt my thought a far off:</hi> Are not theſe the Actions of a free Agent?</p>
                     <p>Moreover, <hi>A. B.</hi> denyes the Juſtice of GOD, which ſhe learned from the peſtiferous <hi>Socinus, L. de Serv. p.</hi> 1. <hi>C.</hi> 1. &amp;c. Where he Sophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally argues, becauſe GOD is Love, 1. <hi>John</hi> 4 8 Therefore there is no vindicative Juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice in him, which is defended by the <hi>Ap. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 22 where he affirms that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which ſpeak of GOD'S Juſtice and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37722:20"/>diſpleaſure in threatning and puniſhing of ſin, are to be underſtood, as theſe which attribute humane parts and paſſions to him.</p>
                     <p>All this contradicts the Scriptures, which teach, that hatred of ſin and vindicative Juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice are of the nature of GOD as he is Simple, Pure, Holy and Righteous, even as Love and Mercy, are of his Nature and Eſſence as He is good. <hi>Habb.</hi> 1.13. <hi>HE is of purer Eyes than to behold Evil and cannot look upon Iniquity.</hi> GOD hath no parts at all, nor paſſions, and when they are aſcribed to Him in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſuch as Love, Anger, Hatred &amp;c. It is ſpoken by Us, not for the infirmity of affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but for ſome likeneſs of His works and ours, as <hi>St. Aug. wordeth it. De Civ. D. L.</hi> 9. <hi>C.</hi> 5. And the effect hath produced the word Revenge which truth of the vindicative Juſtice of GOD, is clearly vindicated from all the Objections of <hi>Socinus by John Owen Diatr. de Juſt. Div.</hi> where he proveth, that the applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or exerciſe of GOD's eſſential Juſtice is to be underſtood when he puniſheth ſin, as our ſoveraign LORD and Judge, and likewiſe he removeth the miſtakes of <hi>Rutherford and Twiſſe,</hi> thereanent, and the ſatisfaction of CHRIST, wherein yet they were not of the mind of <hi>A. B.</hi> and the <hi>Socinians.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Then for the Bleſſed Trinity in the GOD-Head,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37722:21"/>Head, her Doctrine is plainly Heretical, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that it is a Romiſh Errour, to ſay, there are three Perſons in the GOD-HEAD; that there are in Him only three Powers, Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes or Properties of Truth, Righteouſneſs and Goodneſs, and that her ſelf had theſe three Properties. <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 2, <hi>p.</hi> 109, and <hi>pt.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 166 <hi>Lavie continue, p.</hi> 553, 554, <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 3, <hi>p.</hi> 80, <hi>Ap. pt.</hi> 2, <hi>p.</hi> 84, 85.</p>
                     <p>Theſe Sentiments (ſo called by the <hi>Ap.</hi>) are contrary to the Eſſentials of Religion, to the Creed, and to the conſtant Doctrine of the Catholick Church. See ſome of many Scriptures, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7. <hi>There are three that bear record in Heaven, the</hi> FATHER, <hi>the</hi> WORD <hi>and the</hi> HOLY GHOST, <hi>and theſe three are One. Heb.</hi> 1, 3. CHRIST <hi>is the expreſs Image of His</hi> FATHERS <hi>Perſon,</hi> ſee alſo how the Trinity was manifeſted at Chriſts Baptiſm <hi>Mat:</hi> 3, 16, 17. The Father ſpeaking from Heaven, the Son preſent in Perſon, and the Holy Ghoſt by a Dove. So Preaching and Baptiſing are enjoined in the expreſs naming of the Trinity or three Perſons, <hi>Mat:</hi> 28, 19. And thus the bleſſing is ſtill pronounced 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 13, 14.</p>
                     <p>The Primitive Church ſtill condemned all <hi>Antitrinitarians,</hi> for <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and particularly <hi>Sabellius</hi> and <hi>Samoſatenus,</hi> were accurſed by
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37722:21"/>the great Council of <hi>Nice, Anno</hi> 325 <hi>Theodoret Eccl. hiſt. L.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>Epiph. haer.</hi> 6. For the very Doctrine now revived by <hi>A. B.</hi> That there were not three Perſons, but three Names, and three Powers in the GOD-HEAD. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as to exclude all <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and to mantain the Unity of Faith in the Catholick Church, it was expreſſed in all the approven Creeds, which are Exegetick or Explicatory of the Apoſtles Creed, <hi>To wit, the Creeds of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cills of Antioch, Nice and Conſtantinople and of St. Athanaſius.</hi> That there are in the GOD-HEAD three Perſons or Subſiſtencies, having Incommunicable Perſonal Properties, the Father begetting the Son, the Son begotten, and the Holy Ghoſt proceeding from them both, three in One, and One in three, undivided in Eſſence or Subſtance, with much more which is to be ſeen in them to this purpoſe.</p>
                     <p>So that it is evident. <hi>A. Bs.</hi> Doctrine is inconſiſtent with the Scriptures, and many Articles of the Creed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="number">
                     <head>NUMBER II. <hi>Of</hi> CHRIST, <hi>and His Satisfaction for Us.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IT is worthy the noticeing in the firſt place, anent this foundation of Religion, that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37722:22"/>
                        <hi>A. B.</hi> in all her Books never once giveth CHRIST his due Tittles, as it is in the Creed, <hi>His only SON Our LORD,</hi> or, <hi>the LORD,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11, 23. The <hi>Ap:</hi> is guilty of the ſame omiſſion, till <hi>p:</hi> 406. Some approver of <hi>A. B.</hi> in a Letter to the <hi>Ap.</hi> doth it.</p>
                     <p>And no marvel, that they ſhift to ſpeak of Chriſts Divinity, ſince they write, that He had a ſinful Nature, corrupt and rebellious to the Superiour part of His Soul, produceing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations and temptations to ſin, though He conſented not thereto, <hi>S. V. pt:</hi> 1, <hi>p:</hi> 198. <hi>Ap: pt:</hi> 2, from <hi>p:</hi> 198, to 143.</p>
                     <p>This contradicteth the Holy Scriptures, which ſhew clearly, that he took to Himſelf our Nature, but without ſin, which could not have been, if any ſin had been in His Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; for the very firſt motions or inclinations in Us to ſin, (which School-Men call <hi>Primo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primi</hi>) they are ſins, becauſe of our ſinful Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, even before we deliberatly conſent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, <hi>Jam:</hi> 1, 15. <hi>Luſt when it is conceived bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth ſin. Gen</hi> 6.5. <hi>Every Imagination of the thoughts of Mans Heart is only evil continually.</hi> Whereas it was impoſſible, that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt could have had a ſinful Nature, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Divinity, (which is Holineſs and Purity it ſelf) could not have been Hypoſtatically united to his Humane Nature, neither could
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:37722:22"/>the Holy One, <hi>Immanuel,</hi> GOD with us, have any inclination or temptation to ſin in his Nature or proceeding from any thing in Himſelf, as the Scriptures teach us, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. <hi>He was made ſin for us, who knew no ſin. Heb.</hi> 4.15. <hi>He was in all Points tempted like as we are; yet without ſin.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The foreſaid Errour of <hi>A. B.</hi> is a great one but behold a greater! Againſt the Satisfaction which Chriſt the Redeemer made to Divine Juſtice for us. That there was no need for Chriſt to become Man to ſuffer or die for our Redemption, that He had been Incarnat tho Man had never ſinned, to converſe with us viſibly upon Earth, that GOD was not ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by His ſufferings, and that he ſuffered only by accident, for the inſtruction of Men and their relief, and to give them a good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 139. 140. 141. 142. and <hi>pt.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 53.</p>
                     <p>This <hi>Heretical Doctrine</hi> is catcht from <hi>Photinus,</hi> and from <hi>Socinus L. de Serv. c.</hi> 3.4 <hi>&amp; per tot.</hi> That <hi>Arch-Heretick,</hi> and Heir of <hi>Arrius,</hi> who denyed the Divinity of Chriſt, and is the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the <hi>Atheiſts</hi> that now infeſt many places in <hi>Europe,</hi> whether they call themſelves <hi>Deiſts, Theiſts, Unitarians,</hi> or under whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Denomination they paſs at the Time.</p>
                     <p>The foreſaid Doctrine is no leſs Abſurd and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37722:23"/>Heretical, when it proceeds from <hi>A. B.</hi> and her adherents, than as it is diſſeminated be the <hi>Socinians,</hi> who pretend to be Chriſtians as well as they, for they all ſtrick at the root of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> teaching, that Chriſt ſuffered for our behoof, but not in our ſtead; that it is enough to ſay, He ſet Captives free, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>Redemption</hi> imports, paying of the Ranſom alſo for us, both of them, deny the Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Juſtice of GOD, pretending to cry up his Love, and though they pretend to the higheſt Reaſon, yet how unreaſonable is it to ſay, that the SON of GOD, ſuffered as He did without a neceſſity of ſatisfying the Juſtice of GOD thereby, and ſuffering of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of Puniſhments due to Us for Sin: And without which all Mankind had periſhed eternally, as well as the Devils.</p>
                     <p>It was the admirable free Love of GOD, which made the Difference, and it is the great Foundation of Saving Faith, <hi>That when we were ſinners, outlaws and rebells, Chriſt dyed for Us,</hi> Rom. 5.8.</p>
                     <p>Now I ſhall cite the Scriptures for the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of Chriſt, whereby I am perſwaded, that the Impartial Reader will eaſily perceive, that the foreſaid Doctrine of the <hi>Socinians</hi> and <hi>A. B.</hi> is inconſiſtent therewith; and ſo incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the Creed and the Eſſentials of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37722:23"/>Religion, notwithſtanding of her Profeſſion, and her <hi>Ap.</hi> to the contrary.</p>
                     <p>John 10.25. <hi>I lay down my Life for my Sheep.</hi> Mat: 20, 28. <hi>The Son of Man came, to give his Life a Ranſome for many.</hi> Acts 4, 12. <hi>There is none other name under Heaven given whereby we muſt be ſaved.</hi> Gal: 3, 13. <hi>Chriſt hath Rdeemed us from the Curſe of the Law, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made a Curſe for us.</hi> Eph 5, 2. <hi>Chriſt hath given himſelf for us, an Offering and a Sacrifice to GOD:</hi> 1 John 2, 2. <hi>He is the Propitiation for our ſins.</hi> Rev. 5, 9. <hi>Thou haſt Redeemed us to GOD by thy Blood.</hi> Theſe Texts pondered. It may probably ſeem ſtrange, to ſome who raſhly were taken with <hi>A. Bs.</hi> Books, how any Chriſtian could have written ſo perverſely of Chriſt as is forementioned, but they may marvel the leſs, when they finde her writting very often liker to an Infidel than a Chriſtian, as when ſhe aſſerts that <hi>Mahometans</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> may be ſaved, by reſigning their wills to GOD, without mentioning Faith in Chriſt, that the <hi>Jews</hi> are yet the People of GOD, that they love GOD more than any other People, that their being deſpiſed may perhaps ſatisfie for putting Him (GOD) to Death, and that their hopes of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> yet to come is well founded on the Word of GOD. <hi>L. W. pt</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 127, 131, and <hi>pt.</hi> 3, <hi>p.</hi> 3. 168.</p>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:37722:24"/>
                     <p>How can the <hi>Jews</hi> be the People of GOD, who were caſt off for their Infidelity in <hi>S. Pauls</hi> days? <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.15. If the Love of GOD which <hi>A. B.</hi> boaſts of ſo much be of that kinde with the <hi>Jews</hi> love to GOD, then it is but a lifeleſs Fancie inſtead of the true Love of GOD, ſince the <hi>Jews</hi> have not Faith in Chriſt, and <hi>True Faith worketh by Love. Gal.</hi> 5.6. (of which in a number a part af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards) neither <hi>Jewes, Gentiles, Mahometans,</hi> or any <hi>Infidels,</hi> can reſign their will to GOD, (remaining <hi>Infidels</hi>) ſo it is nonſenſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnancie in the adject, to write, that they doe; for none can be <hi>Accepted of GOD but by Faith in his beloved Son the only Mediatour. Eph.</hi> 1.6.</p>
                     <p>What a rare piece of confidence is it for <hi>A. B.</hi> and the <hi>Ap.</hi> to aver that they own the Creed and the eſſentials of Religion, and to mantain the direct contradiction thereof? for if the <hi>Jewes</hi> expectation of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> yet to come be well founded on the Word of GOD (as ſhe ſayes in the fore cited place) then the Chriſtian Belief is not well founded thereupon, that in the fulneſs of time (as <hi>Gal:</hi> 4.4.5.) he was conceived by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and born of the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> and the reſt of the Articles of the Creed concerning Him are falſe, if <hi>A. B.</hi> ſpeak Truth. For the <hi>Meſſiah</hi>
                        <pb n="37" facs="tcp:37722:24"/>to have already come, according to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies in the Scripture, and performed the work of our Redemption in the exerciſe of His three fold Office, and to be yet to come, as the <hi>Jewes</hi> vainly expect, is a flat contradic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: nor can I conjecture, what the wit, or cunning of any <hi>Ap.</hi> can anſwer for <hi>A. B.</hi> in theſe things, unleſs it be ſaid, that <hi>A. B.</hi> is generally miſunderſtood, for her Chriſt is not our Chriſt, mentioned in the Belief, who was Prophecied of in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> and of whom the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> is an Hiſtory. But her Chriſt, is an imaginary Chriſt, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from <hi>Adam</hi> before the Woman was made, and came not of the Seed of the Woman, L. <hi>Etoile dumatin p.</hi> 32.33. and <hi>Ap. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 47. And to evite a very ſtrong Argument againſt her fantaſtical Chriſtianity, taken from <hi>Gen:</hi> 3 15. which is the firſt promiſe of Chriſt, importing the very tenor of the Covenant of Grace, ſhe brings forth a rare ſort of new coined blaſphemy (like <hi>John of Leyden, or Nailour the Quaker,</hi> who called themſelves the <hi>Meſſiah</hi>) ſo ſhe affirms, that ſhe is <hi>That Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Seed, which ſhould bruiſe the Head of the Serpent, L W. pt</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 47. This is that <hi>A. B.</hi> of whom <hi>De Cort.</hi> her admirer ſays, <hi>Pref. to the L. W. p.</hi> 41. <hi>That no Body ſince the Creation of the World Explaines the Scriptures ſo well as
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:37722:25"/>ſhe doth,</hi> but behold what it comes to!</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Ap. pt.</hi> 2. from <hi>p.</hi> 90. to the 100 uſeth much Art to ſmooth the Doctrine of <hi>A. B.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Satisfaction of Chriſt. He diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth a mans being ſubſtituted to ſuffer for another, and declares, that <hi>A. B.</hi> held ſuch a ſubſtitution to be falſe and diabolical, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures a diſcharge to the Party offending, but granted a ſubſtitution of love, whereby Chriſt merited, that we ſhould by our penitence merit Salvation, adding our own merits to Chriſts Sacrifice, to ſatisfie the Juſtice of GOD, and mockes at a man who declares, he is but a frail creature, and hopes to be ſaved by faith in Chriſt; whereas it is manifeſt by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures alreadie cited, and many more which could be ſhown that Chriſts ſuffering in our ſtead, and thereby procuring to us remiſſion of ſin, and freedom from the Puniſhment due to us therefore, is a moſt true and Divine ſubſtitution, and not falſe and Diabolical, as <hi>A. B.</hi> ſaith. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19 <hi>GOD in Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concileth the World to himſelf, not imputing their treſpaſſes unto them,</hi> and not to impute to us our treſpaſſes, is to procure a diſcharge of the ſamen.</p>
                     <p>A wiſe man ſhould not be ridicul'd for his wiſdom, but this is the wiſeſt Courſe, that a ſinner can take, to confeſs his own frailty,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37722:25"/>and believe to be ſaved by the free Mercy of GOD, for the ſake of Chriſts Merits. We do not deny a ſubſtitution of love (as he calls it) that of GOD'S free love in Chriſt Jeſus, whereby we are both Juſtified and Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, but neither Penitence, nor any other Grace beſtowed upon us can be called our Merit; nor can there be any addition made to the Sacrifice of Chriſt, which ſatisfied the Juſtice of GOD, and is the only meritorious cauſe of our Juſtification.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Ap.</hi> inſiſts, ſaying, that we carp at the words <hi>Merit</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> while we grant the thing imported thereby, that Chriſt by his Merits hath procured to us to do penitence and to imitat himſelf, without which non can be ſaved by faith in Him.</p>
                     <p>This is the ſubſtance of all his ſuppoſitions, or imperfect ſort of Argument, in the foreſaid place, which in the Schools is called, a <hi>Sorites.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To which I anſwer briefly, that the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox have good reaſon to quarrel both at the words and the thing which he underſtands thereby, for it is ſimply impoſſible, that ſinners can either ſatisfie the Juſtice of GOD or merit their own Salvation: becauſe there is no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutative Juſtice betwixt GOD and Man, as there is in Contracts between man and man, ſo that it were injuſtice not to remit ſin, upon
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:37722:26"/>all the penitence or good works that we can do, He being infinitly Holy: and we but frail Creatures, who at the beſt are but <hi>Unprofitable Servants Luke</hi> 17.10. We ought indeed to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence our Faith by a good life, but to call our penitence or love to GOD, or imitation of Chriſt our own merit, is but a vain glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riation, and derogatory from the ſatisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Merits of Chriſt; for which I remit him to <hi>Bellarmin, who is a great Orator for humane merits, but confeſſeth, that for the uncertainty of our own Righteouſneſs, and the danger of vain Glory, it is moſt ſafe, to place our whole confidence in GOD'S Mercy alone, and his Goodneſs, and a few lines after, he ſayes, that without a Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation no man can know aſſuredly himſelf to have true Merits; or that he ſhall perſevere in them to the end. Likewiſe becauſe nothing is more eaſie in this place of tentation, than pride to ariſe from the conſideration of good works. R. Bell. Card. Jeſu. de Juſti. L. 5. c. 7. p.</hi> 1266 in 80.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="number">
                     <head>SECTION IV. SUBS. I. N. III. <hi>Of Mans future State.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IN the Seventh and two laſt Articles of the Apoſtles Creed, ſundry great Truths are included, anent Mans future State, which
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:37722:26"/>are clearly taught in the Scriptures, and are of the eſſentials of Religion; namely, that after Death neither Soul nor Body periſh, but they ſhall be joined again by the power of GOD, through Jeſus Chriſt at the Generall Reſurrection, and ſet day of Judgment, when He ſhall pronounce a righteous Sentence upon all Mankind, giving unto thoſe who have done well, Eternal. Life in Heaven, and to the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nal Damnation. But <hi>A. B.</hi> makes a ludicrous Scene of all this, writting, that the World ſhall not be conſumed by fire, there ſhall be no judgment after Death, nor a ſet and appointed day of Judgment nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort of judgment, than what is begun thirty Years agoe, that good People ſhall not goe to Heaven, but Chriſt (coming with men and not with Angels) ſhall dwell with them viſibly for ever on Earth, where they ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate their kinde Eternally, being retired into a ſafe Corner of the Earth, or rather to the Centre of their Soul, to live in all pleaſure, and the Wicked to another Corner of it, to be afflicted by Serpents and all evil things.</p>
                     <p>And ſhe believes all this better than all the other Myſteries of our Faith. <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 1. from <hi>p.</hi> 143. <hi>to</hi> 148. <hi>and from</hi> 150. <hi>to</hi> 159. <hi>and from</hi> 168. <hi>to</hi> 170. <hi>and pt.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 131. 132. <hi>and pt.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 146. And all the foreſaid He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:37722:27"/>rapſodie is approved be the <hi>Ap. pt.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 180. <hi>to</hi> 184. the Myſteries of Faith which ſhe doth not ſo well believe as theſe her own whimſies are, the Unity and Trinity in GOD, the Incarnation and Satisfaction of Chriſt, the efficacie of Grace, with the free will of Man, the Reſurrection of the Dead, the Day of Judgement, and Mens then being mandated to Heaven or Hell. Theſe Opinions of <hi>A. B.</hi> are worſe than the Old <hi>Millenar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> who yet were ſtill condemned, by the Orthodox and Catholick Church, which held that the Scriptures in no place promiſed Chriſts dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on Earth Bodily again, but rather the contrary, as <hi>Acts</hi> 3.21. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.2. <hi>GOD that cannot lie,</hi> hath in his Holy word aſſured us, of the Truths which I have rehearſed on this head, which alſo demonſtrates the falſitie of <hi>A. Bs.</hi> Tenets laſtly repeated.</p>
                     <p>John 5.28.29. <hi>The hour is comming in the which, all that are in the Graves ſhall hear His Voice, and ſhall come forth, they that have done good unto the Reſurrection of Life, and they that have done evil unto the Reſurrection of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi> Heb. 9.27. <hi>It is appointed unto men once to die, but after this the Judgment. Acts</hi> 17.31. <hi>He hath appointed a Day in which he will judge the World in Righteouſneſs by that man whom He hath ordained</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.15.16. <hi>For if the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:37722:27"/>Dead riſe not then is not Chriſt raiſed, and if Chriſt be not raiſed your Faith is vain.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Haſting to the coming of the Day of God, wherein the Heavens being on fire, ſhall be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, and the Elements ſhall melt with fervent heat,</hi> there are many parallel places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as <hi>John</hi> 14.3. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.46. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.16.</p>
                     <p>The Sophiſtical ſhifts that are made be <hi>A. B.</hi> and her <hi>Ap.</hi> in the fore cited places, for excuſing their Errours ſhall be eaſily diſcuſſed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Obj.</hi> 1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Heaven is where GOD is, therefore, when Chriſt reigns with his Saints on Earth, there needs no other Heaven.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Its anſwered, neither GOD<hi>'S</hi> eſſential Immenſity, nor His diffuſed Grace, takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the nature of things, or confounds diſtinct places, ſo Heaven is ſtill His Thron and the place of the Bleſſed, and the Earth his Foot Stool.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. If Chriſt doe not reign with His Saints Eternally on Earth, then the Earth was made only for Wicked Men and Devils.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> The Earth was made for GODS People, who ſerve Him on it now in the Land of the living, tho imperfectly, but afterwards they ſhall ſerve Him perfectly in Heaven.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Obj.</hi> 3. Angels propagate their kinde and ſo ſhall Men doe, when the Body ſhall be made Spiritual.</p>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:37722:28"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> That whimſie of Angels propagation, hath been ſtarted by ſome of the wildeſt of School-Men, but was rejected by the moſt Learned and Solid of them, as <hi>Aquinas, Sum. p.</hi> 3.75.7. <hi>c.</hi> Where he proves that <hi>Angels are of different Species.</hi> and <hi>Swareſ. Metaph. p.</hi> 120.121. <hi>That they cannot produce a Subſtance.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Neither is there need of propagation nor of a new Creation of Angels, there being ſo many of them made at firſt, <hi>Dan,</hi> 7.10. <hi>Thouſand thouſands, and ten thouſ and times ten thouſand.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Obj.</hi> 4. GODS works abide for ever and therefore all living Creatures muſt propagate their kinde for ever.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> 1. Theſe words, <hi>For Ever</hi> doe often ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie, no more than a long time.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. GODS Works abide according to his Appointment, ſome for a leſſer, and others for a longer time, ſome materially endure for ay, though changed in the qualities, as our Bodies after the Reſurrection, and other Creatures once made never come to an end, as all Spirits.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. There is no Marriage in Heaven and ſo no propagation, as Chriſt coargued the <hi>Saducees Mat.</hi> 22.30.</p>
                     <p n="4">4 If Devils and Wicked Men ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate for ever, then their Poſterity ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be judged, contrary to the Scriptures which Teach that all ſhall finally be judged, by GOD, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.14. <hi>Jude</hi> 6.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="number">
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:37722:28"/>
                     <head>SECTION IV. SUBS. I. N. IV. <hi>Anent the Love of</hi> GOD.</head>
                     <p>IT is the high pretenſion of <hi>A. B.</hi> through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all her writtings to reduce men to the Love of GOD, and values her ſelf upon it, as if ſhe had been the firſt in her Age, who had taught that ſin conſiſts in a privation of the Love of GOD, <hi>S. V. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 52. That all Chriſtian Writters, and particularly the reformers did not teach the Love of GOD, or they did it dryly and confounded the matter, and her advancing the Love of GOD, is the diſtinguiſhing mark of her writtings from all Syſtems of Divinity, and that all Church Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cills were of the Devil, drawing men from the Love of GOD, <hi>L. W.</hi> 3. <hi>Pref. to the</hi> 3. <hi>pts. and pt.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 45. <hi>and Ap. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>Car.</hi> 1.5. <hi>from p.</hi> 14. <hi>to</hi> 25. <hi>and p.</hi> 78. <hi>n.</hi> 42.</p>
                     <p>Is it not a pitifull Errour in any Chriſtian, to applaud ſuch writters? who under a vain pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of advancing the Love of GOD, do rail at the higheſt rate, againſt all Chriſtian writters without exception, is not that to do what they can to deſtroy all Chriſtianity?</p>
                     <p>Herein they are like the Sea-Monſters called <hi>Syrens,</hi> who by a ſweet voice allure paſſengers,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:37722:29"/>till they get near to deſtroy them,; or like enemies, who ſet out the colours of Friends, to render us the more ſecure till they fall on with deadly weapons. So it is an uſual trick for all, <hi>Hereticks and Enthuſiaſts,</hi> to ſet out for ſome true Hypotheſis, as <hi>Jacob Bhemen</hi> did, by reſignation to GOD, as much as <hi>A. B.</hi> doth by the Love of GOD: But let us ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them well, and it will ſoon be apparent, that their colour is but fairding, and their cant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deceiving, and that they run from one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream to another, and ſo loſs the Truth which is in the midſt; as <hi>Eutyches</hi> refuting <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> did in oppoſition to him, fall into a new He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, anent the Natures of Chriſt, ſo it is exactly in the preſent caſe, the infamous <hi>Gnoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> of Old, and <hi>Antinomians</hi> of late, depraved the Law of GOD, pretending to exalt Faith, and <hi>A. B.</hi> runs to the other extream, out of a pretence to advance the Love of GOD, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitence and imitation of Chriſt, as the means of attaining it, ſhe cryeth up humane Merite and undervalues the Doctrine of Salvation by Faith in Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>Ap. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 25. <hi>Car.</hi> 5.6. Her Doctrine is very unſound and erronious, anent this eſſential Point of Religion; nor did ſhe know what it is to love GOD, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhe vaunteth ſo much, and reproacheth all others, not only as ignorant thereof, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glecting
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:37722:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>that which is the chief thing in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but even as if they were enemies to the Love of GOD, and her ſelf only the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of it.</p>
                     <p>And for the inſtruction, or making good this my Charge againſt her, I ſhall not inſiſt upon omiſſions, as the not deſcribing the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the thing ſhe writes of, ſhewing what is meaned by Love, either as it is a chief paſſion, or Theological vertue, how Faith and Love are compared together, and ſometimes one of them gets the preference, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the other, whether love of gratitude to GOD, or complacencie in GOD be recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, or what are the true tokens of it, <hi>viz.</hi> love to GODS Truth, to his publick Service, to His People and many the like, which ſhe doth not touch, but ſhall inſtance a few of her many miſtakes, anent the Love of GOD, after that I have intimated to the Reader how the laſt Year, I noted ſome things which I found amiſs in a Latine Pamphlet, entituled, <hi>A Colledge diſcourſe of Comparative Theologie.</hi> which ſeems to be a masked abſtract of <hi>Borignianiſm</hi> and particularly in the ſecond note diſcloſed, the Authors Errour in affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Love of GOD is the chief end of Religion, in every ſtate of Man, and all other things but the means of attaining it,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:37722:30"/>which is not true, either in this Life or that which is to come.</p>
                     <p>For the Chief and ultimate end of all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is GODS Glory and ſubordinat there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, is Mans Eternal Salvation. There are three ſpecial Heads of Religion, containing our duty in this Life, things to be believed, things to be done, and things to be prayed for: 1. In order to things to be believed, Faith is the chief Virtue. 2. As of things to be done, Love is the Spring. 3. And true Grace may be called Devotion, in reſpect of things to be asked of GOD, and hath its degree accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly. Neither is Love only the chief end of Religion, in Mans future State of Bleſſedneſs, which conſiſts, not only in the love of GOD, but alſo in the Intuition and Fruition of Him, with ſuitable exerciſes to be known hereafter. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9.</p>
                     <p>Now to prove <hi>A. Bs.</hi> ignorance, of the Love of GOD, it is manifeſt, 1. Firſt in that ſhe ſaid, the <hi>Iewes</hi> have the true love of GOD, who are <hi>Infidels denying the LORD that bought them.</hi> 2. That all Syſtems of Divinity teach nothing of the Love of GOD, that is, all the Creeds, Catechiſms, Confeſſions of Faith, Expoſitions of Scripture, and all other Books that have been written by Chriſtians, Theoretical or Practical, ſince the Apoſtles
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:37722:30"/>Days, are to be thus taxed; who could have written ſo? but either a perſon groſly ignorant of the love of GOD, or elſe extreamly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent, in belying all the Chriſtian writters, ſeeing it is as notour, as that the Sun brings light, that thouſands of Chriſtian writters, and ſome in all Ages (which if need were, could be eaſily named and produced) have written excellently of the Love of GOD, and far better than this roving perſon hath done. Nor is it like, that a Preacher wrote the <hi>Ap.</hi> for elſe he had not accuſed all others of dryneſs. 3. As the pretended inſpired <hi>A. B.</hi> is moſt vain glorious, that ſhe only had diſcovered the Love of GOD to be the great end of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſo is ſhe no leſs proud of the means that ſhe had attained to obtain it, namely, ſuch a penitence, and ſelf denyall as merited remiſſion of ſins, and which ſhould be added to the Sacrifice of Chriſt <hi>Lae. Temoing de verite pt.</hi> 1.59.61.64. and <hi>Ap. pt.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 91.99. But we have not ſo learned Chriſt <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. Pardon of ſin and eternal Life are none of our merit but GOD<hi>'S</hi> free Gifts procured by Chriſts merits. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8. whereof poſſibly more afterwards.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. You have hitherto narrated ſuch inſtances as convince my ſelf of her ignorance in the main point of Religion, whereto a fourth
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:37722:31"/>ſhall be added, which probably will abait the fondneſs of her admirers, if it doth not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether break her party, if they conſider it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, who noticed not before what doctrine ſhe taught; and that is, that every good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian muſt abandon Riches and Honour, and take no more of them but what is ſimply needful for the ſuſtenance of Nature, and that of the leaſt and meaneſt ſort, for the ſtrain of the Doctrine which her Party cryeth up run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thus.</p>
                     <p>A good Chriſtian ſeeks to attain to the Love of GOD in perfection, which to do we muſt renounce ſelf love, and love of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and none can doe that but they who renounce Riches, and take meat and cloathing only to ſuſtain Nature. <hi>S. V. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 58. 59. <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 121. <hi>Ap pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 66. 67.</p>
                     <p>Now let all that have doted upon <hi>Borignianiſm,</hi> prove themſelves to be her true Proſelites, by this plat form of her levelling, which ere they doe, I am of Opinion, ſhe will have but a very ſmall Train of either Sex; As <hi>Henry Martin</hi> ſaid in the Rump Parliament in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> when it was propoſed, to purge it quite of Immoral Men, purge it alſo ſaid <hi>Martin,</hi> of all Knaves and Fools, and then we ſhall have but a thin Houſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="number">
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:37722:31"/>
                     <head>NUMBER V. <hi>Of the Holy Scriptures.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IT is doubtleſs of the Eſſence of Religion, to have right Sentiments of the Holy Scriptures, which are the word of GOD, and the Rule of Religion. But many of <hi>A. Bs.</hi> and the <hi>Aps.</hi> Sentiments, are wrong in this matter, for <hi>Firſt,</hi> ſhe perverts moſt of the Texts, which are cited in her Books, whereof one pregnant inſtance is already ſhown anent <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. <hi>N.</hi> 2. another is, of <hi>Mat</hi> 5.45. <hi>He maketh his Sun to ſhine on the Evil and on the Good,</hi> from which <hi>A. B.</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth, that the Wicked have the true Grace of GOD, <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 43. whereas the words import only, that Worldly things (ſuch as the Suns light) are common both to good and evil People. 2ly. They derogate from the Authority of the Holy Scriptures, which is altogether Divine and Infallible, the <hi>Ap. pt</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 179 <hi>Approves Tereſa a Spainard,</hi> a pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed inſpired Teacher, who when ſhe was urged with that Text 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. <hi>I ſuffer not a Woman to Teach;</hi> did anſwer, that GOD bid her, not to be directed by one paſſage of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for there was a twofold falſehood (if not
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:37722:32"/>rather a lie) in the anſwer of <hi>Tereſe,</hi> for there is a parallel Text to the foreſaid purpoſe 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.34. And GOD bids us be directed by his Word, as well as when it is found in one paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of Scripture, as if it were in twenty, ſo it was the Devil and not GOD, that ſuggeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſuch an anſwer to her. As <hi>Tertul</hi> long ſince wrote, that all Hereticks <hi>Strive to dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate from the Scriptures, and whoſoever doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prave any part of the Scriptures, he rejects all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are all from the ſame Authority, Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Hereſ. de preſcrip. c.</hi> 49. 3ly. They diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regard and contemn the Holy Scriptures.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Diod. Sic. L.</hi> 14. reports, that <hi>Theopompus</hi> a Pagan Hiſtorian, when he had inſerted ſome part of the Holy Scriptures, into his prophane writtings, did run mad. I ſhall not ſay that <hi>A. B.</hi> was mad, but probably ſhe was Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condriack, for writting as ſhe did anent the Scriptures, exhorting people to imitat herſelf, in not reading the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> for twenty Years, and affirming, that ſhe could write ſuch a Book as it, that it was not hitherto under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by any, and only ſlightly allowing people to read the <hi>BIBLE</hi> that are not otherwayes taught. <hi>S. V. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 120. <hi>Ap. p.</hi> 347. <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 120. Whereas, the Holy Spirit, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us, to ſearch the Scriptures daily. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.11. The truely Divinely Inſpired take their
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:37722:32"/>warrand from the Scriptures 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. Though they were immediatly taught of God.</p>
                     <p>And it was a thing more impoſſible for <hi>A. B.</hi> for to write ſuch a Book as the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> than to have joined the land of <hi>Flanders</hi> to <hi>England,</hi> for ſhe could have written ſuch a Book, either by a fallible or an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Spirit, if by a fallible Spirit only, then it could not have been ſuch a Book, which was written by men infallibly inſpired; and not by an infallible Spirit, becauſe ſhe had it not, as is proven <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. Hence may be eſpyed a piece of very goodly confidence in the <hi>Ap. pt.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 179. affirming, that none could vilifie <hi>A. Bs.</hi> way of handling Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but they who have a ſecret diſguſt at it, whereas on the contrary, out of love to the Scripture, I openly diſguſt her abuſing it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="number">
                     <head>NUMBER VI. <hi>Miſcellanies, relating to the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentials of Religion.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THere are many other heads of Doctrine nearly relating to the Eſſentials of Religion ill treated of in the writings
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:37722:33"/>of the Authors whom I deal with; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruptly brought in by them, without any Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical order: ſome of which ſhall be noticed in this laſt Number together, as they have occurred to my obſervation in ſeven diſtinct points, that this <hi>Subſection</hi> concerning <hi>A. Bs.</hi> Eſſentials, may terminate in a certain method.</p>
                     <div n="1" type="point">
                        <head>POINT I. <hi>Of</hi> GOD'S <hi>Decrees, and the Doctrines depending thereupon.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>AS A. B.</hi> hath not written right things of GOD, about the Eſſentials of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſo, nor of the integrals thereof, though there be ſundry of the ſamen, which have ſo near a relation to and connection with the Eſſentials, that by ſound Divines they are truely called <hi>Circa Fundamentals;</hi> For her Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets anent the high and myſterious Decrees of GOD, and many Doctrines depending there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon (ſuch as the Operation of Divine Grace, upon the Will of Man, and the Perſeverance of the Saints) they are (in my Judgement) both contrary to the expreſs Letter of the Holy Scriptures, and the interpretation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:37722:33"/>by the Orthodox Church.</p>
                        <p>For ſhe frequently affirms, in the general, that GOD had no Eternal Decrees, nor prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of the Actions of free Agents; and in ſpecial, that He had no Eternal Decree of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination <hi>L. W. pt;</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 154. which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.11. <hi>The Counſel of the Lord ſtandeth for ever, the thoughts of His Heart to all Generations.</hi> Acts 15.18. <hi>Known unto GOD are all His Works from the beginning of the World.</hi> Eph. 1.4. <hi>Having choſen us in Chriſt before the foundation of the World. Verſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Having Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinated us to the Adoption of Children by Jeſus Chriſt to himſelf, according to the good pleaſure of His Will. and Verſe</hi> 11. <hi>Who worketh all things, after the Counſell of His own Will.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Again <hi>A. B.</hi> writes, that man hath liberty to reſiſt the Will of GOD, <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 192. which plainly contradicteth the Divine Oracle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.19. <hi>Who hath reſiſted His Will.</hi> And linked with theſe Tenets ſhe aſſerts that gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious perſons may apoſtatiſe, and be eternally damned, <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 136. 137. which aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion is inconſiſtent with our LORD's moſt gracious promiſe <hi>John</hi> 10.28. <hi>My Sheep ſhall never periſh.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>In fine; There are diſſeminated throughout all her Books the whole <hi>Arminian</hi> Tenets con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Quin quarticular Queſtion, excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:37722:34"/>that of univerſal Redemption, which why ſhe omitted (imbracing all the reſt) it is not eaſie to conjecture, unleſs it be for her want of Charity to the generality of Chriſtians.</p>
                        <p>And as <hi>A. Bs.</hi> Doctrine in the foreſaid Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets is contrary to the Scriptures, ſo it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Expoſition of theſe and the paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell Texts of Scripture received in the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Church. For it was condemned by the Synod of <hi>Dort, Anno</hi> 1618, both in the complex and in all the 5 heads thereof. Which Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill was conveened purpoſely to put a Stop to the contagious Errours, which were ſpread abroad in the <hi>Belgick-neather-lands by Epiſcopius, Corvinus, Grevinchovius</hi> and other followers of <hi>Jacobus Arminius;</hi> Unto which choſen men were delegated from many reformed Churches, who were well verſed in the Doctrine of the Primitive Church, and every way able Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel, who alſo after conference with the offending Party, upon mature debate and deliberation finding the <hi>Arminian</hi> Doctrine inconſiſtent with the Holy Scriptures, and the Confeſſions of Faith of the Reſpective Churches, and tending to the reviving of the <hi>Pelagian</hi> and <hi>Semi Pelagian Hereſies,</hi> and not a little ſymbolizing with the peſtiferous <hi>Socinians,</hi> did condemn it altogether, as ſaid is.</p>
                        <p>Neither can it be juſtly thought, that theſe
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:37722:34"/>worthy men were ignorant of the ſenſe of the Confeſſions of Faith of the Reſpective Churches to which they belonged, who were all approv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and commended at their return home, both by their Conſtituents, and the King, Princes and States which ſent them, for their actings in that Aſſembly. Nor have the repreſentatives of any Proteſtant Church, ever ſince diſallowed the Acts of the Synod at <hi>Dort;</hi> and altho ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular men, have vented ſome flights and fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies too favourable to the Doctrine of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrants,</hi> that is not to be imputed to any National Church, which by their publick Doctrine and Actings, rather diſapproves than allowes the ſamen.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Scotland</hi> had only at that Synod <hi>Mr. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canquell</hi> (a Pious and Learned Man) to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it, but <hi>England</hi> had four at firſt, <hi>George Biſhop of Landaff, Joſeph Hall Dean of Worceſter and John Davenant,</hi> afterwards Biſhops, who are and will be ſtill famous in the Church of Chriſt, for their labours in the work of the Goſpel; and particularly, for their excellent writtings, <hi>Dr. Ward</hi> was the fourth, and <hi>Dr. Goad</hi> was ſent over in ſtead of <hi>Joſeph Hall,</hi> when he came home ſick.</p>
                        <p>Yet I own, that it was both Piouſly and Prudently done by the Church of <hi>England</hi> with the conſent and authority of our Wiſe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:37722:35"/>and Learned King <hi>James</hi> the 6. to prohibite all raſh Preaching or Writting, (excepting ſuch as ſhould be authoriſed thereto) on theſe abſtruſe and intricat queſtions, raiſed be the <hi>Arminians</hi> upon the heads aforeſaid, and when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they might be obliedged to touch upon them, in explaining a Text of Scripture to a popular auditory, to hold to Scripture lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and the words of the 39 Articles and the approved homilies of the Church.</p>
                        <p>Many judicious People marvel, how any man could have been at the pains, to write ſo large a Book (being tedious to be read) as the <hi>Ap.</hi> for <hi>A. B.</hi> is; but I finde that his plea for <hi>Arminianiſm,</hi> in ſundry parts thereof hath very much conduced to ſwell it to the bigneſs, that it hath accreſced to under his pen; as <hi>pt.</hi> 2. from <hi>p.</hi> 104. to 127. and <hi>pt.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 386. 387. and often in other places thereof.</p>
                        <p>Wherein he hath ſtudied, to repreſent the poſitions and Arguments of the <hi>Arminians</hi> in behalf of <hi>A. B.</hi> in a taking popular dreſs; yet in all his pleadings to that purpoſe, I have not been able to diſcover any Argument which is new, but what hath been often toſſed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, and ſolidly anſwered and diſcuſſed by the Orthodox Writters: which to repeat from them, conſiſts not with my Scope in this place.</p>
                        <p>But to ſhew, that his arguing can be ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:37722:35"/>anſwered, I ſhall only at this time deal with one of his moſt plauſible Topicks which <hi>pt.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 112. is propounded thus.</p>
                        <p>GOD knoweth all things only according to their nature; but the Will of Man being made a free faculty to chuſe, or not to chuſe, or to reject any object propounded unto it by the Underſtanding, GOD doth not fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>know what it ſhall determine, ever as a man who giveth the power of his goods to his Wife, cannot fore-know how ſhe will diſpoſe of them.</p>
                        <p>This is but a meer fallacie from the homo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomie or different ſignifications of the words <hi>Knowing</hi> and <hi>Nature, For GOD ſeeth not as Man ſeeth,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.7. And He is Nature natureing, Mans Knowledge of things is but finite and limited, as himſelf is, apprehending things to be of ſuch and ſuch a nature, by the properties figure, habitudes and effects, which he diſcerneth them to have, and were it not for theſe means of Knowledge they would define things otherwiſe, whereas the omniſcient GOD, in whoſe eternal <hi>Idea</hi> all things had their firſt determinations, knoweth all things compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſively, even all the poſſible cauſes, effects and contrariety of things, ſo of all Agents whether neceſſary or free, <hi>HE knoweth our thoughts afar off. Pſ.</hi> 139.2. GOD who In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:37722:36"/>the Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> to tell <hi>Hazael,</hi> what his free will would determine, long ere he knew ſo much himſelf 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.12.13. <hi>He that teacheth man knowledge ſhall he not know? Pſ.</hi> 94.10.</p>
                        <p>Neither doth his ſimile hold, for a wife is her Husbands equal, to whom he may give power of his goods, either prudently or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudently but the alwiſe GOD, hath not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted any of His Creatures from the reach of His Omnipotencie or Omniſcience. The due conſideration of the infinite difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween GODS Omniſcience and Omnipotence, and the Faculties of ſinfull man ſerves alſo to diſcloſe the grand <hi>Arminian Errour,</hi> in ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending his Grace upon Mans free Will, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Eſſentials of Religion.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="point">
                        <head>POINT II. <hi>Of the Image of</hi> GOD <hi>in Man.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>A. B.</hi> aſſerts that the Image of GOD after which Man was created, conſiſts only in Mans free will, and nothing elſe. <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 42. which is contrary both to Scripture and Reaſon, for the Soul of Man being Spiritual and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:37722:36"/>imports as much of the Image of GOD, as free Will doth, and the Scriptures ſhew plainly, that it conſiſted in Knowledge, Righteouſneſs, Holineſs and dominion over the Creatures. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. <hi>Let Us make Man after our own Image, and let him have dominion</hi> &amp;c. Eph. 4.24. <hi>Put on the new man, which after GOD is created in Righteouſneſs and true Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> Col 3.10. <hi>Renewed in Knowledge after the Image of HIM that created Him.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="point">
                        <head>POINT III. <hi>Q. If Man ſinned before he ſinned.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>AS the Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi> mocked the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of <hi>Baal,</hi> for their ridiculous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.27. So it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable, that having read many ridiculous things in the Books of <hi>A. B.</hi> to ſtate the Queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this point <hi>Ironically</hi> againſt her, which according to her Doctrine, muſt be anſwered poſitively, that Man ſinned before he ſinned, that is, that he ſinned before GOD gave out the Law, which he tranſgreſſed, ſince the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dequate definition of ſin is, tranſgreſſion of the Law of GOD, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Where no Law is, there is no tranſgreſſion,</hi> but behold what
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:37722:37"/>
                           <hi>A. B.</hi> teacheth, againſt this fundamental truth! <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 2. That <hi>Adam</hi> inclined to ſin before the Law was given, and before the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was made (which was not on the ſixth day) which abſurd Doctrine the <hi>Ap.</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends <hi>pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 59. Saying that GOD did not give Man a Law, till he ſaw him depart from the Love of GOD to the love of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and follow his own will. All which falſe Sentiments the <hi>Diſcurſor Academicus</hi> affirms to be moſt probable, <hi>p.</hi> 5. But I am certain, that it is not only improbable, but alſo moſt untrue, for every inclination in us to ſin is ſin, as contrary to the rectitude and intire Holineſs and Obedience, which GOD requires of us.</p>
                        <p>Moreover, their foreſaid Tenet contradicts the hiſtorical account of the firſt ſin, and Mans fall from the eſtate of Innocencie, given by GOD himſelf, that it was by tranſgreſſing that Sacramental or trying Commandment, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the Covenant of works, <hi>Not to eat of the Tree of Knowledge of Good and Evil upon pain of Death, Gen.</hi> 2.17.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="point">
                        <head>POINT IV. <hi>Of Perfection.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THere is nothing more readily to be read in the Books of thoſe that are ſwelled with Spiritual pride, Uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritablneſs,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:37722:37"/>Malice, and Hypocriſie, than the pretended Perfection of themſelves and their Partie; and among the reſt <hi>A. B.</hi> and the <hi>Ap. pt.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 131. to 137. and <hi>p.</hi> 4.32. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouch, that they can be perfect; keeping all the Commandments of GOD, becauſe all his Commands are preſtable, or GOD hath given no Commands, but what its poſſible for man to fulfill. I ſhall not gainſay, but <hi>A. B.</hi> might fancie her ſelf to be perfect, in her notion of perfectneſs, by culling out ſome Commands of GOD, and neglecting the reſt <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 205. (contrary to <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.10.) and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, that they might be ſound Believers, who obſerved none of the Articles of Faith. <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 173.</p>
                        <p>All which pretended perfectioniſts make an unanimous outcry, againſt the Aſſemblies Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm, which we uſe, for affirming, that no meer Man ſince the fall, is able in this life perfectly to keep the Commandments of GOD.</p>
                        <p>But their Clamour is groundleſs, becauſe, the plain and ſound ſenſe of the foreſaid anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer in the Catechiſm is, that GOD in the ordinary diſpenſation of his Graces, hath ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver given ſuch a meafure of Grace to any man, nor promiſed to free him of ſin, alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in this life, ſo that he can perfectly and abſolutly fulfill his Law, but thorow
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:37722:38"/>Chriſt who fulfills it in and for us, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.7.8, 9. The Law ſhews our duty, which we ſhould ſtill endeavour to fulfill, aiming at Perfection, and what we cannot do, to lippen to GODS free Mercy, and Chriſts merits, to perfect it for us, as if we had attained to Perfection our ſelves.</p>
                        <p>For the Queſtion is nor, what GOD may do in this matter, but what he is pleaſed to doe; He might (if He had pleaſed) have kept <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſtill alive on Earth, who probably was perfect, when Chriſt raiſed him from the Dead, and ſo were the Saints who aroſe <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.52. But we cannot expect the like, but pray by Faith for what the Law requireth, as <hi>St. Bernard</hi> writteth in <hi>Gan. Serm.</hi> 50</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="point">
                        <head>POINT V. <hi>Of Perſeverance.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>ONE of <hi>A. Bs.</hi> Sentiments is, that the moſt Perfect Saints, may apoſtatiſe, or fall from the eſtate of Grace, and be eternally damned <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 136.137. which her <hi>Ap.</hi> Homologateth <hi>pt.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 136.</p>
                        <p>And albeit this be one of their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines, which depends upon another Errour,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:37722:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>of their denying all the Eternal Decrees of GOD formerly noticed, (<hi>po.</hi> 1.) yet it ſeemed neeeſſary, to obſerve it here by it ſelf, becauſe the abſurdity thereof may be more eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned by the Unlearned than ſundry others of the <hi>Arminian Chain,</hi> which are more abſtruſe.</p>
                        <p>It is indeed lamentable, that the beſt of Saints, through negligence, when tempted to Sin, and the Infirmity of their nature, may ſometimes fall into ſinful acts, and remain ſo a ſpace, without effectual Repentance, yet it is manifeſt by Divine Light, from the Holy Scriptures, that the truly Godly do not fall away totally and finally, from the eſtate of Grace, <hi>But the foundation of GOD ſtandeth ſure, the LORD knoweth who are His,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. His by Predeſtination, or an Eternal Decree of Election in Chriſt Jeſus, who are given to Him in the unalterable Covenant of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and are <hi>Cleanſed from all ſins by His Blood.</hi> 1 John. 1.7. Of whom it is written, <hi>Rom;</hi> 8.29.30. <hi>Whom He did fore know, them He alſo Predeſtinated, Called, Juſtified and Glorified.</hi> And of all theſe the LORD promiſeth <hi>John</hi> 10.28. <hi>My Sheep ſhall never periſh, I will give unto them Eternal Life.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Perſeverance is an unſeperable effect of Sanctifying Grace, the habit whereof, being once planted by the gracious hand of GOD
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:37722:39"/>in a Mans Soul, never dyeth, although it may ſo appear by ſome ſinful acts, as Herbs and Trees which are bereaved both of fruit and flouriſhing in the Winter ſeaſon, this is called, <hi>The Root of the matter,</hi> which remained in the Gracious and Patient (tho under ſharp tryals, ſometimes repining) <hi>Job, ch</hi> 19.28. And to this purpoſe the Prophet <hi>Micah</hi> 7.8. <hi>Rejoice not againſt me O my Enemie when I fall, I ſhall ariſe.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>How inconſiſtent with this foundation of Religion, are the writtings of <hi>A. B.</hi> and her <hi>Ap.?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="point">
                        <head>POINT VI. <hi>Anent the Sacraments.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>ANent the Sacraments, <hi>A. B.</hi> is as Erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious as in the Points forementioned, writting, that to obtain Salvation we need not pray, nor go to Church, nor take the Sacraments, but only be Paſſive, <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 102. Proteſtants go about the LORDS Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per without Devotion, <hi>L. W. Pref. to pt.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 4. To baptiſe Children is from the Devil, <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 31.</p>
                        <pb n="67" facs="tcp:37722:39"/>
                        <p>Did ever the practiſe of any perſon contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict his profeſſion; more plainly, than the <hi>Ap.</hi> and his <hi>Virgin Patroneſs</hi> do, who ſolemnly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, that they ſhall own the Scriptures, for the Teſt of their Doctrine, which yet is againſt them, almoſt in every point, as for this in hand, concerning the Sacraments, have we not as luculent Precepts for the conſtant uſe of them as of any other duties? <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Go teach all Nations baptiſing them &amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23. <hi>I have received of the LORD, that which alſo I delivered unto you, and</hi> V. 26. <hi>As often as ye eat this Bread and drink this Cup &amp;c. A. B</hi> did ſnatch the <hi>Objection,</hi> againſt the baptiſing of Infants, from the <hi>Socinians and Anabaptiſts,</hi> which is moſt frivolous, that it is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in expreſs terms in the Scriptures. <hi>Origen</hi> who lived in the ſecond Centurie writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.5.6.7. Aſſureth us, that the <hi>Church had it always, and that by tradition from the Apoſtles,</hi> Yet are we more ſure, that it is a clear conſequence from the Scriptures. which being natural from the Text, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtorted, doth ever import a Scriptural truth, As we read, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.29. Our Saviour charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Saducees,</hi> anent the great Article of the Reſurrection, <hi>That they did err not knowing the Scriptures,</hi> albeit, not the expreſs words of the Text, (<hi>Exod.</hi> 3.6.) which he cited, were
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:37722:40"/>directly againſt them, but the conſequence thereof, ſo upon this ſound foundation, Infant Baptiſm is firmly grounded, for the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are not only Signs, but likewiſe Seals of the New Covenant, and they to whom the gracious promiſes and conditions of the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Charter belong, have a right alſo to the Seals appended thereunto, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7.10 <hi>The Promiſe is to Thee and thy Children</hi> ſaid GOD to <hi>Abraham.</hi> Baptiſm comes in the place of Circumciſion, which was adminiſtred to Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, when eight days old. The right Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Word and Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, are the ordinary means of our Salvation, and undoubted marks of the true Church.</p>
                        <p>The <hi>Ap. pt.</hi> 2 <hi>p.</hi> 154. to 159. Alleadgeth what he can, to juſtifie <hi>A. B.</hi> in this, which doth not ſatisfie.</p>
                        <p n="1">1 That ſhe was above Ordinances. Which is a vain boaſting and contrary to GODS di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection <hi>Gant.</hi> 1.8.</p>
                        <p n="2">2 That ſhe durſt not go to the <hi>Popiſh Churches,</hi> for fear of her life; She could not be in alike hazard every where, and how doth that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe her, for teaching, that no Bodie needs go to Church, or partake of the Sacraments!</p>
                        <p n="3">3 That ſhe wrote a Book in defence of the Sacraments, againſt the <hi>Quakers.</hi> The <hi>Quaker</hi>
                           <pb n="69" facs="tcp:37722:40"/>who offended her was rebuked therefore by his Partie, and they were reconciled with <hi>A. B.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>And at the beſt ſhe contradicteth her ſelf in this Point.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="point">
                        <head>POINT VII. <hi>Of</hi> Paſtors <hi>and Church Government.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THe ſuppoſed Gentle-woman, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Illuminated <hi>A. B.</hi> and her Defender or <hi>Ap.</hi> (transforming them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into Angels of Light <hi>S. V. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 112) in all their writtings about Religion, have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulged the ſwing of their abſolut and indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent free will in nothing more, than in their ranting and railing, at the <hi>Paſtors of CHRISTS</hi> Flock and the Church Government. For, thus they write, that it is unlawful, for any to make it a trade (or office) to teach others. <hi>S. V. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 115. <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 3 <hi>p.</hi> 90. The office of a <hi>Prieſt</hi> is an enemie to the reſignation of Souls to GOD, and <hi>Ap. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 53. All the evils of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> comes from the <hi>Paſtors,</hi> and all the Peoples degeneracie, from their Guides. I could adduce many more paſſages to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but it is needleſs, when the <hi>Ap. pt.</hi> 2.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:37722:41"/>
                           <hi>p.</hi> 158. declares that the <hi>L. W.</hi> (which is the chief of <hi>A. Bs.</hi> Books, the Key and Rule of all the reſt) was written on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe againſt the <hi>Paſtors,</hi> becauſe of the degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie of the <hi>Roman Church.</hi> Hereupon it may be reflected without debaiting, if ſhe was not injurious, to write ſo againſt all the <hi>Paſtors of the Church of Rome,</hi> without exception of any, how can it be thought true, that ſhe wrote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Paſtors</hi> of that <hi>Church</hi> only, ſince ſhe declares the <hi>Paſtoral-Office</hi> it ſelf to be unlawful, and declaims as much againſt <hi>Proteſtants</hi> as <hi>Papiſts</hi> and beſides them, all <hi>Paſtors</hi> in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> not excepting any, either in the <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Abaſſine Churches,</hi> or any where elſe in the World! But on the matter it ſelf, how contrary is their Doctrine to the Holy Scriptures. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are well inſtructed, that the Alwiſe GOD (who made Man a ſocial Creature, naturally inclined to ſociety, and thereby needing both Laws and Government) did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways preſcribe Laws to Mankind, and for the benefite thereof, poſitively appointed, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment both Civil and Eccleſiaſtick, and by a ſpecial deſignation, <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Church-Officers</hi> for his own immediat ſervice, and the Salvation of Peoples Souls. Eph. 4.11.12.13 <hi>He gave Paſtors and Teachers, for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:37722:41"/>for the edifying of the Body of CHRIST, till we all come in the unity of the Faith, and of the knowledge of the SON of GOD, unto a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of CHRIST.</hi> Heb 5.4. <hi>No man taketh this honour upon himſelf, but he that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> called of GOD, as was Aaron.</hi> Where the true <hi>Paſtor</hi> is, there the true Church is; and when the Shepherd is ſmitten, the Sheep are ſcattered abroad, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.31. So it is one of the main Policies of Satan, for deſtroying the Church altogether, to endeavour to bring all the <hi>Paſtors</hi> under contempt, as a fit mean for ſubverting the office it ſelf, and conſequently to ruin the Church of CHRIST. Such rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt all <hi>Paſtors,</hi> and the Sacred Func<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it ſelf, is as <hi>A flood of water caſt out of the mouth of the Old Serpent,</hi> the accuſer of the Brethren, for <hi>To drown</hi> (if he could) <hi>the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who is cloathed with the Sun,</hi> that is the Church of GOD. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.9.10.15.</p>
                        <p>The accute <hi>Ap.</hi> when he readeth this part of the <hi>Advertiſement,</hi> may poſſibly ſay, that the language ſavours of too much paſſion, and the inference is too hard; for, may not <hi>A. Bs.</hi> words bear a more favourable interpretation? ſuch as that of the <hi>Diſc. Academ p.</hi> 16. &amp; 23. That <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Church Government, Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> and the publick Worſhip of GOD, have
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:37722:42"/>no certain connexion with Mans Salvation, nor are they certain neceſſary and infallible means of recovering the love of GOD, and <hi>A. B.</hi> one where or another, of her writtings, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth the Office of <hi>Paſtors,</hi> as a thing that may be reformed, and to ſay, that Sacred Offices or means ordained by GOD for his own Glory, and Mans Salvation, may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, is a more moderat Sentiment (to hold their phraſe) than that they are ſimply unlawful, and ſhould be quite aboliſhed.</p>
                        <p>Hereto it is anſwered, that I deſigned in this Cenſure, to evite all hard words, as much as poſſible could be, without prejudice of truth, which is herein defended; yet it is allowed as a maxime among moraliſts, either in ſpeaking, writting, or other actions to ſharpen reaſon, not by our own paſſions or affections, but by theſe which the cauſe requireth.</p>
                        <p>I called her writting on this point againſt the <hi>Paſtoral Office,</hi> Ranting, becauſe her lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage to that purpoſe, is the ſame with that of the wild Sect of the Ranters; and railing which is calumniating, or a wrongous ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racteriſing, and aſcribing undue epithites to good things.</p>
                        <p>I have noted on <hi>Diſcurſus Academicus,</hi> his errours in this matter, neither have I read in any Book of <hi>A. B.</hi> where ſhe retracteth the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:37722:42"/>foreſaid errours, and if the <hi>Ap.</hi> hath done it, he ſhould have told us of it.</p>
                        <p>Now to put a period to the firſt Subſection, anent the eſſentials of Religion, it is manifeſt, I hope, by what I have written (to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Reader) that <hi>A. B.</hi> had no good skill of Religion, were it but for one reaſon that ſhe preferred <hi>Heatheniſm</hi> to <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> by aſſirming, that <hi>Heathens, Turks</hi> and <hi>Jewes,</hi> had more reaſon and Religion than <hi>Chriſtians, Pref. L W. p.</hi> 9.10. And that not one Chriſtian, is ſo much reſigned to GOD, or did under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand true vertue ſo well, as the <hi>Heathens</hi> did. <hi>pt.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 129. And ſince her Sentiments, are againſt the Holy Scriptures, and the eſſentials of Religion, ſhe hath not repreſented the ſame aright, nor revived the Spirit of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, neither was ſhe Divinely Inſpired to publiſh the Goſpel to the World; which was the thing thus to be demoſtrated.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="subsection">
                  <head>SECTION IV. SUBSECTION II.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="number">
                     <head>NUMBER I. <hi>Of Acceſſories in the General.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe <hi>Ap. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8. and 9. comprehends all the Doctrine of <hi>A. B.</hi> in the two general heads, of the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentials
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:37722:43"/>of Religion, and her acceſſories, which diſtinction I promiſed to examine in this place. <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. <hi>Subſ.</hi> 1. <hi>Initio.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The word Acceſſory, which is taken from the Latine word Accedo, ſignifyeth, ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to come to, to follow, or add to any thing, but in the Engliſh (for the moſt part) it ſoundeth ill, to be acceſſory importing, the abetting or partaking of a Crime.</p>
                     <p>In the civil Law it ſignifies an Adminicle or Addition to a ſtatute of which it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, that it be not alien from or contrary, but that it follow the nature of the principall to which it is an Appendix. <hi>De regulis juris in ſexto reg.</hi> 42.</p>
                     <p>But in Divinity few or none ſound writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters uſe the term Acceſſory, in comparing points of Religion among themſelves, the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary diſtinctions are, of Eſſentials and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grals, of things neceſſary and expedient.</p>
                     <p>Eſſential or fundamental points are the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines clearly revealed in Scripture, and upon which the Holy Ghoſt (the Revealer) hath put the caracter of neceſſity to be believed for Salvation, as the ſum of the Creed is; The Integrals, are other Doctrines taught by GOD to make up the whole, as the ſeveral parts of Mans Body, make the compoſition of Man intire, ſo the uniform obeying all the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:37722:43"/>Commandments of GOD, make up the whole of Religion. Again the Articles of Religion, are either the neceſſary and indiſpenſable means of obtaining the chief ends thereof, <hi>to wit,</hi> GODS Glory and Mans Salvation, ſuch as Faith, Hope, Love, and Repentance, or they are neceſſary by Reaſon of the Precept, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe commanded by GOD, ſuch as the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and the publick and ordinary Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of GOD.</p>
                     <p>And further, all things commanded by GOD, are called neceſſary, and things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined by the Church for Edification, Order and Decency, are ſaid to be of poſitive right and expedience.</p>
                     <p>And ſome things not fundamental which are but darkly revealed in Scripture, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians may keep Peace, and have communion together, albeit they have different Opinions thereanent, as in points of Diſcipline, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which whoſo would be fully informed, he may read <hi>Iſaak Cauſabon,</hi> on the Epiſtle of <hi>King James</hi> the 6th to <hi>Cardinal Perron</hi> anent the Peace of the Church.</p>
                     <p>But <hi>A. Bs.</hi> Acceſſories can no wayes be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, to any of the foreſaid branches of the points of Religion, as being either neceſſary, true, lawful or expedient, which ſhall be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted in the next number. Neither is it
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:37722:44"/>obvious (viewing all Chriſtian Churches) to find out a parallel to <hi>A. Bs.</hi> notion of Acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſories, but that which it moſtly reſembles, is the decretals, wherewith the modern <hi>Romaniſts</hi> have ſtuffed the Canon Law, of which it is truely ſaid, that the Old Decrees had been good, if they had wanted the Alae, Wings, and new additions forced upon them; So her repreſenting the Eſſentials of Religion, and preſſing of Piety had been good if ſhe had underſtood them well, and done it without diminution of any, or adding extravagant flights and fancies, to wing them throughout the whole World in her own conceit.</p>
                     <p>There remains yet to be diſcuſſed another ſenſe of the word Acceſſories, and that is, in military terms, Auxiliaries or additional forces are called Acceſſories, but there can be no reaſonable tranſlation, of this to <hi>A. Bs.</hi> purpoſe, for the Truths of Religion contained in the Holy Scriptures, are perfect and ſufficiently able to ſerve their turn, to defend themſelves, and to make the man of GOD perfect unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, without ſuch additions or auxiliari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es as ſhe propoſeth.</p>
                     <p>For they are but meer intruders, coming un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called, over which a vigilant eye ſhould be had, leſt (if intertained or let alone) they prove, ſuch auxiliaries as the <hi>Mammaluks</hi> did in
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:37722:44"/>
                        <hi>Egypt,</hi> and the <hi>Saxons</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed and ſubverted the Natives whom they came to aid, becauſe, both their Principles and Intereſts, were contrary to each other.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Obj.</hi> O but (ſays the <hi>Ap. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 45. There is no ſuch evil to be feared from <hi>A. Bs,</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſories, for they tend to advance the main ends of Religion, and tho they be not war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randed in the Scriptures, yet they are neither hurtful nor damnable.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> To anſwer which <hi>Objection</hi> ſhall be the ſubject of the following Number of this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Subſection</hi> anent her Doctrines.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="number">
                     <head>NUMBER II. <hi>Of</hi> A. Bs. Acceſſories <hi>in particular.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IN this inqueſt all the Doctrines of <hi>A. B.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to and depending upon the Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials of Religion might be reviewed, ſince the <hi>Ap.</hi> comprehends the whole of her Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine in theſe two, Eſſentials and Acceſſories, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out noticing the third branch of the diviſion, namely Doctrines, which (tho not Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal or Eſſential) yet may either further or
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:37722:45"/>prejudge the Eſſentials of Religion, as they are either true or falſe, proper to Religion or improperly muſtered therewith; but that being in a good part done already, <hi>Subſ.</hi> 1. <hi>n.</hi> 6. wherein it is proven in ſeven Points, that many of <hi>A. Bs.</hi> Doctrines, which are nearly related to the Eſſentials of Religion, are very erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious and diſproven of the Holy Scriptures. I proceed now to examine other Doctrines which ſhe reckoneth not among the Eſſentials of Religion and ſo they muſt be indeed her Acceſſories.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That Man before he ſinned did feed, upon the quinteſcence of things (being altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Spiritual) he could flee in the Air, and go to the Centre of the Earth, and ſo it ſhall be with Man afterwards, when Chriſt reigneth upon Earth with the Saints. This Doctrine is diſſeminated throughout all <hi>A. Bs.</hi> writtings, and approven be the <hi>Ap. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 46. 47. which is not ſo innocent, as he repreſents it, but is both hurtful and damnable.</p>
                     <p>For it contradicteth the truth of the Hiſtory of the Creation of the World, written by <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Book of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> be the dictating of the Holy Ghoſt, which (accomodating to Vulgar Capacities, mentioneth not as other Scriptures doe, the Creation of Angels or Spiritual beings) aſſure us that Mans Body was
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:37722:45"/>material, <hi>Formed of the Duſt of the Ground, Gen.</hi> 2.7. His food was material, and the forbidden fruit was alſo ſuch, <hi>Good for food and pleaſant in the Eyes. Gen.</hi> 3.6.</p>
                     <p>Which could not have been, if Man had been altogether Spiritual, and in the future State of Glory Man will need no material food, whether, we call it the eſſence or quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſcence of things materiall, but he will be as the Angels of GOD.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That all Men may forſake the Truth, <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 33. This is a falſe Doctrine, for if all Men ſhould forſake the Truth, the Church might fail, which is impoſſible, <hi>It being built upon the Rock of Ages, againſt which the gates of Hell ſhall never prevail.</hi> Mat. 16.18. And wherewith our LORD JESUS CHRIST, <hi>will be preſent to the end of the World. Mat.</hi> 28.20.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That Infants dying before they come to the exerciſe of Reaſon, are either good or bad, and conſequently muſt be ſaved, or dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, according to the will of their Parents. <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 6.7.8.9. and <hi>pt.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 155. This is againſt the Principles of Religion, of GODS Election, and the tenor of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Antichriſt is the Devil, <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 32. and the Devil is nothing. <hi>S. V. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 94. Theſe Tenets are overthrown by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:37722:46"/>which teach us plainly that <hi>Antichriſt is a man or a ſet of men ſitting in the Temple of GOD.</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. That perſons reſigned to GOD return to ſuch an eſtate of perfect innocencie, as <hi>Adam</hi> was in before the fall, <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 138. Which is an unſound Doctrine, ſince <hi>Adam</hi> at firſt was altogether free of Sin, which can be ſaid of no Saint in this Life, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.2.</p>
                     <p>It is manifeſt by what is already written on this ſubject, how eaſie it were to expoſe the abſurdity of all <hi>A. Bs.</hi> Acceſſories, but they are ſo many, that to go through them all particularly (even according to the preſent method) adding a ſhort refutation to every one of them, would require as much writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, as was deſigned for this whole Tractate. Therefore having excerpted, from the Books of <hi>A. B.</hi> and the <hi>Ap.</hi> ſome ſcores of Acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſories, like theſe forementioned, equally hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to Religion, and noted exactly in a paper, apart, the places where they are to be found; I ſhall here (for brevities ſake) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce <hi>Twenty</hi> of them as a ſwatch of the reſt, reaſonably hoping, that every Chriſtian Reader, who is acquainted with the Holy Scriptures, and being thereby inſtructed, that <hi>Hay and Stuble, are not fit materials for the building of GOD.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11.12.13. Will be able
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:37722:46"/>at the very recitation thereof to confute them himſelf, without my help, which GOD wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling afterwards ſhall (if it be needful) not be wanting, in the behalf of Truth, or it will be done by abler Pens, which the Church will never be deſtitute of.</p>
                     <p>And theſe <hi>Acceſſories</hi> are.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>That there are no true Chriſtians now in the World.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>The ordinary ſins of Papiſts are the ſins againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>Proteſtants diſown the civil Magiſtrat.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4. <hi>A Spiritual Man is never melancholly.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5. <hi>A Spiritual Man will not take a walk for recreation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">6. <hi>Mentall Prayer ſhould be omitted.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="7">7 <hi>Sin is only a diſorder of the five Senſes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="8">8. <hi>All the advantages that Men reap from others ſerves but for their damnation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="9">9. <hi>The Devil at firſt moved men to poſſes their own Goods.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="10">10. <hi>It had been good there had never been Schools nor Learning in the World.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="11">11. <hi>GOD'S curſing the Earth made mans returning to GOD the more eaſie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="12">12. <hi>GOD calls no man to any place of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or Power.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="13">13. <hi>CHRIST'S Kingdom comes not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſecond Petition in the LORD'S Prayer.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:37722:47"/>
                     <p n="14">14. <hi>GOD doth not permit ſin.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="15">15. <hi>Good motions incite alwayes to ſuffering.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="16">16. <hi>Phiſitians and Divines doe ordinarily more ill than good.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="17">17. <hi>The Devil inlightneth our Uunderſtanding, and maketh us conceive deep Divine Myſteries.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="18">18. <hi>We ſhould not commend good things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Devil can do ſo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="19">19. <hi>We ſhould not inſtruct others but when they deſire it.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="20">20. A. B. <hi>was Divinely Inſpired in all things to reform the World.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It is no leſs than a ſpectrous piece of goodly confidence, which ſheweth it ſelf in all the writtings of <hi>A. B.</hi> and the <hi>Ap.</hi> to affright people into the belief of their viſionary Doctrines (in ſtead of giving ſolid reaſons for them) ſtill to cry, that ſhe was Divinely Inſpired.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Obj.</hi> 1. For how (ſay they) could it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be, that ſhe who was unlearned, did write of ſo many things, and rare verities, and in ſuch a raviſhing ſtrain, beyond the reach of the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Divines? So that to offer to correct her Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, is no leſs preſumptuous, than to dare, to correct the Spirit of GOD, and whoever op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth her Sentiments, are like <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres,</hi> that withſtood <hi>Moſes,</hi> like the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who oppoſed CHRIST himſelf, or like the <hi>Jewes, Atheiſts,</hi> and <hi>Hereticks,</hi> that
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:37722:47"/>contradicted and perſecuted the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and primitive Chriſtians.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> 1. That is ſufficiently already anſwered, in the third <hi>Section,</hi> where it is proved at large, that ſhe was not Divinely Inſpired; but ſince they ingeminat it ſo often, ſome more ſhall be ſaid to it here.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. To diſcover, oppoſe and confute Errours in any perſons Books is not to oppoſe the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of GOD, but rather to be led by the famen, for GOD is Truth, and whoſoever defends the Truth is on his ſide.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Good words and a zealous ſtrain of writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting are only good, when Truths and no fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities are thereby expreſſed, for the moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious writters that ever exiſted in the World, ſeemed to affect a pious ſtrain, and mixed many Heavenly like words with their poyſonous po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, to cover from the unadvertent the Venom thereof, ſuch as <hi>Gelſus, Porphyrie, Julian, Vaninus,</hi> and in fine, <hi>Heretickes, Shiſmaticks, Sectarians,</hi> and <hi>Enthuſiaſts,</hi> in all their writtings.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. For <hi>A. Bs.</hi> pretending to have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, and her crying down all Schools and Learning, ſhe had many (infamouſly) famous impoſtors for Precedents, who to impoſe their damnable Doctrines and deluſions on the World, declaimed loudly againſt all Learning as their moſt deadly enemy, ſuch as the <hi>Gnoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:37722:48"/>Montanus, Manes and Mahomet.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5. CHRIST and his faithful Servants were oppoſed by many, in all Ages, ſlighted and perſecuted for holding the Truth; but it is an undue thing, for <hi>A. B.</hi> to compare her ſelf to them, and her Oppoſers to their perſecutors, when ſhe is confuted and contemned only, for teaching Errours; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20. <hi>For what glory is it, if when ye be buffeted for your faults, ye ſhall take it patiently?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">6. The Cabine of <hi>A. Bs.</hi> rarities can be diſcloſed, without a miracle, or flying ſo high as to Divine Inſpiration, for a key to open it.</p>
                     <p>For moſt of her extravagant flights, anent Mans primitive Eſtate of Innocencie, and the future ſtate after the day of Judgement, have been catcht (with little variation) from the <hi>Jewiſh Cabala.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It was formerly ſhowen <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. <hi>Subſ.</hi> 1. <hi>n.</hi> 3. how the exotick opinions of ſome School-men, gave her wrong Sentiments of Angels, in like manner hearing of ſome nice points debated among School men and Philoſophers, ſhe was apt to adopt the worſt ſide of the Problem, which being once made hers, out it flyes into the World, as a new revealed verity, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, <hi>A. B</hi> teacheth <hi>S. V. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 96. <hi>And the Ap. homologates, pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 62. That both our Souls and Bodies are propogated, from
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:37722:48"/>
                        <hi>Adam.</hi> Contrary to <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9. where GOD is called the <hi>Father of Spirits,</hi> or the creatour of our Souls, in contradiſtinction to our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural parents, who are there termed the <hi>Fathers of our fleſh.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And many other of her Acceſſories, ſhe might have learned by ordinary diſcourſe, as that the <hi>Heretick, Eunomius,</hi> and generally the <hi>Gnoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> out of a pretence of magnifying Faith, ſaid, that good works were not neceſſary. This falſe and odious opinion her <hi>La.</hi> (after her charitable manner) doth moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently father upon all <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> without due conſideration, that <hi>St. Aug.</hi> confuted it. <hi>L. de fide &amp; oper.</hi> Whoſe orthodox ſtrain is followed by <hi>Calvin</hi> and all <hi>Proteſlant writters,</hi> and <hi>Billarmine himſelf, de Juſtif. L.</hi> 3 <hi>c,</hi> 6. Vindicats <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of the foreſaid imputation.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. It was aſſerted in my hearing by ſome, whom the <hi>Borignianiſts</hi> had miſtuned, that there are more than two thouſand veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, (ſpeaking of theſe Acceſſories) ſet out in the Books of <hi>A. B.</hi> which are not to be read in all the writtings either of <hi>Papiſts</hi> or <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> I have diſcovered in her Books more than an hundreth falſities, but have ſeen none of theſe new diſcloſed verities; and if any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorite of hers, ſhall be at the pains to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:37722:49"/>them, let him take heed that he make not a falſe muſter, or rather ſuch — an appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, as drunken—men ſee of great armies in the Air, which inſtantly, and quite diſappear, when ſober people are curious to view them. And if Acceſſories be called New Verities, they ſhould be rejected on that very head, by reaſon, that no truth can be new, and all Truths are older than Errours.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Obj.</hi> 3. Have there not been ſome perſons Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely Inſpired Teachers in all Ages, ſuch as <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonie, and Paul the Anachorets, St. Tereſe, St. Briget, and St. Katharine, Theular, and Thomas a Kempeis.</hi> And were it not for fear of your <hi>Paſtoral Office, A. B.</hi> would be reſpected as one of theſe, and her Books held worthy of all acceptation.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> 1. There ſhould be no ground to fear, the falling of the <hi>Paſtoral Office,</hi> altho many now living were inſpired, in the meaſure of the Prophets and Apoſtles (which will never be, ſeeing the Canon of the Scriptures is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat) becauſe the <hi>Paſtoral Office</hi> is appointed of GOD, for his eſpecial Service, and his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual preſence is promiſed to be therewith, even as if a King ſhould reveal his will ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſome ſpecial favorits, it would no wayes follow from thence, that the ſtanding Laws ſhould not be the peoples Rule, and be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, and executed by the ſettled Judges.</p>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:37722:49"/>
                     <p n="2">2. None of theſe were infallibly inſpired, and no more was <hi>A. B.</hi> neither do I read, that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Anthonie</hi> the Egyptian Monks ſpake againſt the eſtabliſhed Offices in the Church, though they chuſed a Monaſtick Life, in time of Perſecution.</p>
                     <p>If <hi>A. B.</hi> had any Precedent, it was the <hi>Spaniſh Nun Tereſa,</hi> who yet pretended not to be the ſingular or ſole Doctrix of the whole World, as <hi>A. B.</hi> did.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thomas a Kempis and Teular,</hi> were good men, but why doth not the <hi>Ap.</hi> call <hi>St. Aug. Bernard,</hi> and many more eminent men as well inſpired as they?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Obj.</hi> 4. To what purpoſe is all this reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt <hi>A. Bs.</hi> Acceſſorie Doctrines? Since the <hi>Ap.</hi> did premoniſh <hi>pt.</hi> 1. <hi>Car.</hi> 13. <hi>p.</hi> 38. That if any perſon did not reliſh the Acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſories, he might let them alone, that is to ſay, he ſhall not be bound to believe them, and let him forbear to diſpute againſt them, how much ſoever he be dipleaſed therewith.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> That is a ſhift put into the mouths of all who are become ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hly fond of all <hi>A. Bs.</hi> writtings, but it is ſuch a ſilly ſhift, that I marvel to hear, any rationall perſon, pronounce it for a defence, when he is preſſed with good Arguments, againſt her Errours from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Reaſon.</p>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:37722:50"/>
                     <p>In the common uſe of the phraſe, to let a thing alone, is to forbear or to medle or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern with it, on ſuch an occaſion, as when a Boy is to be chaſtiſed for a fault, he cryes, let me alone, but let us examine the <hi>Aps</hi> own gloſs of the expreſſion.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> he ſays the meaning is, you need not believe <hi>A. Bs.</hi> Acceſſories to be true, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you pleaſe. Here he enjoins a rare thing! Did ever any other perſons pretending to be Divinely Inſpired, in all their writtings, leave the Readers at libertie, to believe the half of them to be true or no! Why did ſhe mix and confound them in all her twenty two Books, with the Eſſentials of Religion, which ought to be believed, and how can unlearned people ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate the Gold from the droſs?</p>
                     <p n="2">2. He ſayes, diſpute not againſt them; ſo ſays <hi>Mahomet in his Alcaron c.</hi> 5. and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; If Truth be in them, it ſhould be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, if falſehood it ought to be confuted, or diſputed againſt, and many of them are ſuch, as is already proven.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Obj.</hi> 5. It hath been ſaid to me, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo writes againſt <hi>A. B.</hi> will be anſwered, even as the writtings of <hi>Le. Clerk</hi> at <hi>Amſterdam</hi> and all <hi>Socinian Books</hi> are ſtill defended by ſome perſons, tho they give much offence to the Church men; were it not better then, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:37722:50"/>diſputing in matters of <hi>Theologie,</hi> than to increaſe it?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> I aprove not <hi>A. Bs.</hi> Sentiments in this caſe, who declares, that the writtings of <hi>Luther, Calvin,</hi> and all the Reformers, (whom ſhe accounts <hi>Hereticks</hi>) ſhould have been quite deſpiſed, and not anſwered, or themſelves cut off. <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 27. It is our duty to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute for the Truth, and altho Errours have Abetters and defenders, yet the Truth which is ſtronger than Errours, will at laſt prevail.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Obj.</hi> 6. The harmonie or conſent of all the parts of the Holy Scriptures, is one evidence that they were given by Divine inſpiration, ſo <hi>A.B.</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver contradicteth herſelf, which ſheweth that ſhe was led by the Spirit of GOD in all her writtings.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> If ſhe was led by the Spirit of GOD in all her writtings, then ſhe ſhould not be oppoſed, but there is one thing ſaid and another thing ſeen, and her deeds in writting falſities proves her ſaying the contrary to be untrue, one may write Books without contradicting himſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and yet without Divine Inſpiration, but the tryal of that point anent <hi>A. B.</hi> ſhall bring the fourth <hi>Section,</hi> anent her Doctrines to an end.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="number">
                     <head>NUMBER III. <hi>Of her Contradictions.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IF one propoſition be true, then the contradic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory aſſertion muſt be falſe, and no pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liating
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:37722:51"/>or favourable interpretation can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile them; as for Inſtance. That is a moſt true ſaying which alſo is written ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times be <hi>A. B.</hi> that, Man can only be ſaved and juſtified by the merits of CHRIST, but the contradiction of it is falſe, which ſhe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe writes, that we muſt add our own merits to CHRISTS Sacrifice. This contradiction is not taken away by the ſubterfuge of the <hi>Ap. pt.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 98. 99. Where he ſays, her meaning was, that we cannot be ſaved without mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, for mortification is our duty and not our merit, for Mans merit with GOD is Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merical, a thing impoſſible.</p>
                     <p>In the end of the third <hi>Section</hi> it was ſhown how <hi>A. B.</hi> contradicteth her ſelf, anent the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of knowing Divine Inſpiration. And an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other of her contradictions, was hinted in the former Number, in anſwering the fourth <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection,</hi> namly, ſhe ſays, that ſhe was Divinely In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired, to write all her Books, if that ſaying be true then the contradiction of it muſt be falſe, that ſhe wrote the moſt part of them without Divine Inſpiration, which clearly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, from her bidding us let alone her Acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſories, which fill moſt of her Books.</p>
                     <p>To believe and not to believe a Doctrine, is a contradiction, but <hi>A. B.</hi> requires the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of her Doctrine, that fills all her Books,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:37722:51"/>becauſe written by Divine Inſpiration, and yet requires us not to believe her Acceſſories, or the moſt part of her Doctrines, becauſe ſhe wrote them not by Divine Inſpiration, which is a contradiction.</p>
                     <p>I ſhall adduce two or three more of <hi>A. Bs.</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, and then (for the time) let them alone.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. It is affirmed, that many Heathens re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned their wills to God, and were faithful to Him, tho they had no laws whereby to know Him. <hi>L W pt.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 123. but herein ſhe contradic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth her ſelf in the very next page, <hi>viz.</hi> 124. by affirming, that thoſe Heathens had Laws from GOD, with the Doctrine of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Man of himſelf is more inclined to Good than to Evil, <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 2. And yet ſhe writes, that our ſelf-will is capable to move it ſelf only to evil, <hi>L. W. pt.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 76. which is a flat contradiction.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The <hi>Ap.</hi> approves <hi>A. Bs.</hi> crying down all Schools and Learning, Paſtors and Church-Government, and that GOD calls no Man to a place in the Church, and yet he ſays, that he would not ſeperate from a lawful <hi>Biſhop. p.</hi> 349.</p>
                     <p>Where are abundance of contradictions for to have no Church Government, and yet to join with it is a contradiction, ſo to ſeperate from thoſe whom GOD hath not called and not to ſeperate, how contradictious is it?</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:37722:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>SECTION V. <hi>How Errours in Books ſhall be diſcerned.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is ſomewhat difficult, to give certain Rules, whereby any perſon not well verſed in Divinity, can diſtinguiſh Truth from Errour, in reading Books, except the Holy Scriptures, in which there is no Errour at all, but infallible Truth only.</p>
               <p>Yet I ſhall give ſome helps to know what Truths are written in other Books.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Conſider well, if what is written be <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the proportion of Faith Rom.</hi> 12.6.</p>
               <p>For falſe Prophets are known by their fruits, that is, their Doctrine and Actions. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.15. <hi>Luke</hi> 6.45. If they contemn, wreſt or gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay the Holy Scriptures, in the leaſt, they are Erronious.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We are likewiſe premoniſhed from the unerring Canon of the Holy Scriptures, that the teachers of falſe Doctrine are very proud, overveening of themſelves, and undervaluing all others in compariſon of themſelves and their partie. <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 65.5. <hi>Who ſay, ſtand by thy ſelf, come not near to me, for I am holier than thou, theſe are a ſmoke in my noſe, and a fire that burneth all the day.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2.4. <hi>They are proud, boaſters, headie and high minded. ſo</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:37722:52"/>1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Deſiring to be Teachers of the Law, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding neither what they ſay, nor whereof they affirm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Simon Magus</hi> gave himſelf out that he was <hi>Some great one. Acts</hi> 8.9. and the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Hiſtories of the Church have narrated, that both <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> ſtill vented intolerable ſpiritual pride, ſuch as, <hi>Manes, Arrius, Pelagius, Novatus and Donatus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And albeit <hi>St. Paul</hi> declared, that he was not inferiour to the chiefeſt Apoſtles, in vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of his Office againſt the contempt caſt upon it by falſe Teachers; it were moſt impertinent arrogancie, for any now to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to ſuch praiſe, ſince they have not <hi>St. Pauls</hi> infallible Spirit, and an immediat call from GOD to preach and write Books.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is a good Rule, which is written by <hi>Sir Thomas Brown, in his Book of Vulgar Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours. c.</hi> 1. That all deceivers write Sophiſtical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo that any man who is acquainted, with the Rules of Logick, when he readeth erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious arguing, let him try and he will finde it captious and peccant againſt the Rules of true reaſoning, either in the matter or the form, or in them both; where he alſo prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth clearly, by inſtances from the Scriptures that the firſt Sophiſms or fallacious way of argumenting had the Devil for the Author.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:37722:53"/>
               <p n="4">4. All erronious writters uſually hyperbolize too much, through ignorance or ſelf conceit, ſtill running unto extreams, either praiſing or diſpraiſing, to an exceſſive degree; as in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſing avarice, they commend Prodigality, and contrariwiſe, they cannot reprove Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality, without perſwading to penuriouſneſs, but liberality is the virtue in the midſt.</p>
               <p>So the <hi>Circumcellions</hi> of old, thought that the only way to Heaven was by ſuffering, therefore they wandred unwiſely to and fro like mad-men, ſeeking people to kill them, and many writters have fallen into grievous Errours, ſplitting on theſe Rocks, or Shelfs unwarily, like the Ships which ſteering too far off from the hazardous <hi>Shylla,</hi> fall into <hi>Charybdis,</hi> whereas the ſafeſt ſailing is in the midſt, betwixt the two. In like manner we ſee ſome writters, in commending the Love of GOD to derogate from Faith, and good works, they call them merit, whereas the writters of Truth, aim always to give every thing its due praiſe or diſpraiſe without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining from the juſt meaſure, either to the extream of the exceſs or the defect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECTION VI. Q. <hi>If any ſhould read the Books of</hi> A. B.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> THey who are well ſtudied in the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:37722:53"/>Syſtems of Divinity, may profitably read ſome good things in very ill Books, ſuch as the <hi>Turks Alcaron, Socinian-Books, Hobs Laeviathan,</hi> and the Pamphlets of <hi>Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſts,</hi> and ſtill confuting Errours, as they meet with them; but I think that none can ſafely read the Books of <hi>A. B.</hi> excepting only thoſe who can diſtinguiſh Truth from Errour, according to the Rules given in the laſt <hi>Section,</hi> becauſe of the ſnake lurking in the Graſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 1. You deſpiſe the writtings of <hi>A. B.</hi> becauſe ſhe was a Woman. <hi>Ap. p.</hi> 146.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I honour the Sex, but am not bound to approve a Womans Erronious doctrine, ſuch exceſſive reſpect is not due to an <hi>Angel from Heaven. Gal.</hi> 1.8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. <hi>A. Bs.</hi> Books are carped at, as <hi>Philo</hi> the <hi>Jew,</hi> and <hi>Celſus</hi> did with the BIBLE, cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring half Sentences in ſundry places, not heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scope, or looking to what is ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or what followes after, or is explained in other parts of her writtings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That Challenge ſays nothing to one who Cenſures <hi>A. Bs.</hi> Books throughly, hath taken to task her whose <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> and proved that ſhe was not Divinely Inſpired, and erred egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly in her writtings, both anent the Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials of Religion, and all the points thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 3. She wrote well of Love to GOD.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:37722:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> You may read other Books on that ſubject, who have written far better, and are free of errors.</p>
               <p>Neither knew ſhe well the Love of GOD who had not Charity to Man. 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.20</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECTION VII. <hi>If</hi> Borignianiſts <hi>be a New Sect.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe <hi>Ap. p.</hi> 349. denyeth, that they are a New <hi>Sect,</hi> becauſe they provide no Orders for a new Society, forbidding to join with any other.</p>
               <p>I grant they have not done it formally, but doubtleſs they have deſigned it, (when their number ſhould increaſe) ſince they defame all Chriſtian Churches, yet they would think it too ſevere a Cenſure, to compare their pride to <hi>Eroſtratus,</hi> who ſince he could not do any great thing that was good, did burn the Temple of <hi>Diana</hi> at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> only to get himſelf a name in the World.</p>
               <p>I am of opinion, that the followers of <hi>A. B.</hi> ſhall ere long vaniſh away as the <hi>Bhemaniſts</hi> have done, whom I have known to make as great a figure, as the <hi>Borignianiſts</hi> do now, as <hi>St. Athanaſius</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Arrians</hi> (a far more dreadful Party) it will be but a little Cloud, which will ſoon paſs over, (in Latine) <hi>Nubecula citò tranſitura.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>AMEN.</closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:37722:54"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
